<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Pseudochristus: or, A true and faithful relation of the grand impostures, horrid blasphemies, abominable practises gross deceits; lately spread abroad and acted in the county of Southampton, by William Frankelin and Mary Gadbury, and their companions. The one most blasphemously professing and asserting himself to be the Christ, the Messiah, the Son of God who dyed and was crucified at Jerusalem for the sins of the people of God. The other as wickedly professing and asserting her self to be the Spouse of Christ, called, the Lady Mary, the Queen, and Bride, and Lambs Wife. Together with the visions and revelations, to which they did pretend their ways of deceiving, with the names and actions of sundry persons deceived by them. As also their examinations and confessions before the justices of the peace, their imprisonment, and their tryal before the judg of assize, at the last assize holden at Winchester, March 7. 1649. Published for a publique benefit and warning to every one to take heed to himself, that he be not deceived by the errors and deceits of these present times. / By Humphry Ellis, minister of the word in the city of Winton.</title>
            <author>Ellis, Humphrey, d. 1676.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 175 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84383</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E579</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E602_12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206414</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865576</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865576</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117821</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84383)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117821)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 92:E602[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Pseudochristus: or, A true and faithful relation of the grand impostures, horrid blasphemies, abominable practises gross deceits; lately spread abroad and acted in the county of Southampton, by William Frankelin and Mary Gadbury, and their companions. The one most blasphemously professing and asserting himself to be the Christ, the Messiah, the Son of God who dyed and was crucified at Jerusalem for the sins of the people of God. The other as wickedly professing and asserting her self to be the Spouse of Christ, called, the Lady Mary, the Queen, and Bride, and Lambs Wife. Together with the visions and revelations, to which they did pretend their ways of deceiving, with the names and actions of sundry persons deceived by them. As also their examinations and confessions before the justices of the peace, their imprisonment, and their tryal before the judg of assize, at the last assize holden at Winchester, March 7. 1649. Published for a publique benefit and warning to every one to take heed to himself, that he be not deceived by the errors and deceits of these present times. / By Humphry Ellis, minister of the word in the city of Winton.</title>
                  <author>Ellis, Humphrey, d. 1676.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>62, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Macock, for Luke Fawn, and are to be sold at his shop at the sign of the Parrot in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An edition of: Ellis, Humphry.  Pseudo christus.</note>
                  <note>"Grand .. Blasphemies," enclosed in right curly brackets on title page; "Abominable .. Deceits;" by left curly brackets.</note>
                  <note>Final leaf = imprimatur leaf.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May. 27".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Franklin, William, --  ropemaker of Overton.</term>
               <term>Gadbury, Mary.</term>
               <term>Delusions --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Visions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117821:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>PSE<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DOCHRIST<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S:</hi> Or, A true and faithful RELATION OF THE
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Grand Jmpostures,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Horrid Blaſpemies,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Abominable Practiſes</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Groſs Deceits;</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> Lately ſpread abroad and acted in the County of <hi>Southampton,</hi> by <hi>William Frankelin</hi> and <hi>Mary Gadbury,</hi> and their Companions.</p>
            <p>The one moſt blaſphemouſly profeſſing and aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf to be <hi>The Chriſt, The Meſſiah, The Son of God who dyed and was crucified at Jeruſalem for the ſins of the People of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other as wickedly profeſſing and aſſerting her ſelf to be <hi>The Spouſe of Chriſt,</hi> called, <hi>The Lady Mary, the Queen, and Bride, the Lambs Wife.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with the Viſions and Revelations, to which they did pretend their ways of deceiving, with the Names and Actions of ſundry Perſons deceived by them.</p>
            <p>As alſo their Examinations and Confeſſions before the Juſtices of the Peace, their Impriſonment, and their Tryal before the Judg of Aſſize, at the laſt Aſſize holden at <hi>Wincheſter, March</hi> 7. 1649</p>
            <p>Publiſhed for a publique Benefit and Warning to every one to take heed to himſelf, that he be not deceived by the Errors and Deceits of theſe preſent times.</p>
            <p>By HUMPHRY ELLIS, Miniſter of the Word in the City of <hi>Winton.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>This day is a day of trouble, and of rebuke, and of blasphemy: for the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are come to the birth, and there is not ſtrength to bring forth. <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſ. 37.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Then if any man ſhall ſay unto you, Lo, here is Chriſt, or there; believe it not. For there ſhall ariſe falſe Chriſts, and falſe Prophets. Behold, I have told you before: <bibl>
                  <hi>Mat. 24.23, 24, 25.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Macock,</hi> for <hi>Luke Fawn,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the ſign of the Parrot in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:117821:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:117821:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous and Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Here preſent to thy view a very ſad ſtory, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains in it a Relation of ſuch and ſo high impieties, that like thereunto in all things hath not been yet heard of, to have been acted amongst us in this Nation: The importunate deſire of many Chriſtian Friends, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and others, the expectation of all the Country hereabout, and the right information of others, (who living at a distance, even in remote parts of the Nation from us of this place, unto whom ſome rumor of theſe things have come, and who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſire to be more fully informed concerning them,) have required, called for, and neceſſitated the publiſhing thereof. And that the publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hereof, hath been by me thus undertaken and performed, hath not been from any great willingneſs of mine own thereto, but that by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of Friends I have been neceſſitated unto it, alledging, that by reaſon of my living and constant reſidence in this City, where much of theſe things have been acted, by reaſon of my acquaintance alſo with the Juſtices, and with divers other perſons abroad in the Country, I might be beſt furniſhed with Informations for the carrying of it on, and that it was therefore rather expected of me then of any other. It hath been alſo much urged, that great benefit might come to the publique hereby, that it might be a ſpecial means to warn others to beware of theſe or the like de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, that they be not deceived by them. Theſe Reaſons, eſpecially the latter, have wrought upon me, to appear in publiſhing thereof, though cenſures enough for my pains herein is that which at leaſt is from many to be expected by me. And now, Reader, if there be any love and zeal in thy heart to the Honor of God and Christ, thou wilt here ſee matter of Lamentation, that amongst us who profeſs his Name, any ſhould ariſe in ſo high a manner to blaspheam his Name: Of Lamentation alſo for the ſad Condition of our Nation, that ſuch abominations are to be found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst us. Here mayſt thou ſee what a root of bitterneſs that unlimit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, lawleſs, boundleſs Toleration is of all Religions, and of all things what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever under pretence of Religion, which ſome under colour of liberty of conſcience have contended for: What bitter fruits would ſoon ſpring from it, may be hereby eaſily diſcerned. Haſt thou any interest in God and Chriſt? ſee what cauſe there is that thou improve it, in thy ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117821:3"/>to the Throne of Grace, and that not only in behalf of our Land, that it may by his Grace be ſpared, notwithſtanding theſe and the like evils committed in it; but alſo, that God would be pleaſed to rebuke this Spirit of Error and Blasphemy that is thus gone forth, and ſpreads it ſelf amongst us; That God would alſo make his own people to be of one heart, and to ſtrive earneſtly for the Faith of the Gospel, to contend for the Faith once given to the Saints. And that thou mayſt reap benefit from this Diſcovery, which is for thy benefit intended, and make that uſe which God would have thee to make thereof, is the deſire, and ſhall be the prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Lord Jeſus, and Work of the Goſpel, HUMPHRY ELLIS.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Wincheſter, <date>May 14. 1650.</date>
                  </hi>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POST-SCRIPT.</head>
            <p>WHat is here diſcovered in the enſuing Relation, I was for a great part an eye and ear Witneſs thereof; other things I had from their Confeſſions in their Examinations before the Juſtices, and from the Teſtimonies of divers perſons of known honeſty and integrity, whoſe Teſtimonies, ſubſcribed with the hands of thoſe from whom I received them, I have reſerved by me. Conſidering then that I have ſuch Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities for the things here reported, which are not things reported to be done far off, like the ſtories of ſome travellers, which if falſe, yet could not be eaſily disproved; nor done long ago, as things forgotten, out of the memory of man; but things done among our ſelves, and that very lately, that they are freſh in the memories of moſt perſons hereabout, that very eaſily I might be disproved, ſhould any other things then what are true be reported by me; and queſtionleſs this book will come into the hands of ſuch who would be very glad of ſuch an advantage, as to be able to charge any untruth upon it: On the other ſide, thouſands in theſe parts can witneſs theſe things for the generallity and ſubſtance of them to be true, that therefore I hope none will ſee any cauſe to question the truth and credit of the things here related, how ſtrange ſoever they might otherwiſe ſeem to be unto them.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:117821:3"/>
            <head>A true and faithful Relation of the grand Jmpoſtures, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>WHat our bleſſed Saviour hath foretold to his Diſciples, ſhould come to paſs in the latter Times, and to be a great and manifeſt ſign of his Coming, and of the end of the World, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That men ſhall ſay, <hi>Lo, here is Chriſt, and lo there: that falſe Chriſts, and falſe Prophets ſhall ariſe; Mat.</hi> 24.23, 24. the ſame may be ſeen truly verified in theſe times of ours; and the fulfilling thereof, even in the literal ſence of it, will be diſcovered in this following <hi>Relation.</hi> Although I may herein make diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of the ſinful, erroneous, Heretical and Blaſphemous Opinions, ſpeeches and practiſes, of divers perſons; yet <hi>William Franklin</hi> and <hi>Mary Gadbury,</hi> (the one profeſſing himſelf to be <hi>The Chriſt,</hi> the other as blaſphemouſly proclaiming him ſo to be; and both of them joyning together, and effectually prevailing, to the ſeducing of the Souls of divers, to follow them in their ways of deſtruction;) are the perſons whom I ſhall eſpecially deal withall; and whoſe ways and practiſes of deceiving, with what hath been done by and upon them within theſe few moneths paſt in this County of <hi>Southampton,</hi> I ſhall endevor to lay open and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover. But as that which may give ſome light to the following Relation, and the better direct all that may ſee or read it, what uſe they are to make of it, it will be neceſſary that I firſt of all make ſome diſcovery of theſe Perſons, their Conditions, Callings, and manner of living in Times paſt; the way and means of their acquaintance together, and aſſociating them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in ſo ſinful a manner, and for ſo wicked an end, to and with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with the occaſion of their coming together into this County, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that underſtanding thereof I have received, either by their own Confeſſions, or the informations, which thoſe to whom they or ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them have been formerly well known, have given me concerning them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Franklin,</hi> a man, as may eaſily be gueſſed, much about fourty years of age, was born at <hi>Overton,</hi> a place not far from <hi>Andover</hi> in this
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117821:4"/>County of <hi>Southampton,</hi> was an Apprentice in <hi>London</hi> to the Trade of a Rope-maker, hath been about theſe ſixteen years a married man, and hath at this time a wife and three children living in <hi>Stepney</hi> pariſh, near <hi>London,</hi> the place of his habitation, where he hath both lived and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, till of late, the Trade to which he was Apprentice.</p>
            <p>For his manner of living, he hath been well eſteemed in Times paſt, as a civil man, diligent in his Calling, honeſt in his dealings, careful to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for his Family, and hath born Office in the place and pariſh where he hath lived; yea, he hath been well eſteemed in Times paſt for Religion, having been an eminent Profeſſor of it, very zealous in the duties of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and very conſtant in the practiſe and obſervance of the Ordinances of the Goſpel: I have received very good teſtimony concerning him, that he hath been eſteemed by the godly as an eminent Saint, as a choyce Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor of godlineſs: he hath been of late years much afflicted, his Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly viſited with the peſtilence, himſelf alſo (as I have heard) ſick of it: he was alſo in a condition of deſertion, doubting of the love of God, but had afterwards reviving by the Promiſes of grace applied to him; beſides ſickneſs both in body and minde, he hath been ſomewhat diſtract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his brain: I have ſeen it teſtified under the hand of <hi>Charls Stamford,</hi> Chirurgion, that in the year 1646. <hi>William Franklin</hi> was diſtracted, that he had bled him divers times, and uſed other means for that diſtemper: This of his diſtemper I the rather write concerning him, that I may not be cenſured to conceal any thing that might in the leaſt extenuate his offences, eſpecially ſeeing that ſeveral Certificates concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this his diſtempered condition were preſented in his behalf, when he ſtood at the Bar before the Judg at the Aſſize; and intimating that what was done by him to be while he was in diſtracted fits. Yet this I muſt alſo add, That I finde not thoſe <hi>Certificates,</hi> which I have ſeen, to certifie any thing directly of his being in ſuch a diſtemper ſince the year, 1646. While he hath been in priſon in this City, I have ſeveral Times ſeen him, and had concerning his Opinions and Practiſes much conference with him, but could never ſee or hear ought from him, which might argue him in the leaſt to be ſo diſtempered; but rather in ſuch a cautious wary manner ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing himſelf, that what ever he ſpake, was ſufficient to ſhew him to be a man all this time in a ſober minde, enjoying the right uſe of his <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectuals,</hi> his underſtanding faculty, according to the ſtrength of thoſe parts he was endued withall, very free from any ſuch natural diſtemper. And though I have alſo ſpoken with divers, that have ſeveral times talked and converſed with him ſince his coming into this Country, yet I never heard of any to declare, that any thing in all this time hath been ſeen or heard to proceed from him, which might argue him ſo diſtempered: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117821:4"/>for theſe Reaſons thus expreſſed, although I cannot but ſay, the man hath been mightily poſſeſſed with a ſpiritual frenzy, in what hath been declared and done by him; yet I cannot admit any thing of ſuch a natural diſtemper to be alledged to extenuate theſe great evils which he hath faln into.</p>
            <p>But to return to that Relation of him whence we have thus digreſſed: In that affliction and diſtemper of his before mentioned he fell into divers ſtrange temptations; and many blaſphemous paſſages and expreſſions, ſaying, <hi>That he was God, that he was Chriſt,</hi> fell from him, and were uttered by him: but he afterward recovered from that diſtemper and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction of body and minde, and both diſcerned and acknowledged that <hi>Satan</hi> had attempted to bring him under ſtrong deluſions: he began to follow his Calling again, he went to the Congregation, or gathered Church, to which he did belong, and whereof he was a member, and there humbly and graciouſly, to the apprehenſions of thoſe that heard him, acknowledged to the glory of God, and his own ſhame, that he had ſinned, and blaſphemed God, and was held for a time by <hi>Satan,</hi> and his own heart, under that ſtrong deluſion: he declared how God deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered him, he warned all to keep cloſe to the written Word of God, to watch and pray, that they entered not into <hi>temptations;</hi> and to take heed they were not led away from the <hi>Truth</hi> by the error of the wicked, and ſo did fall from their own ſtedfaſtneſs. After this, he walked ſometime in fellowſhip with that Congregation, and there was great hope that he was now well recovered from ſuch deluſions; but however not long after he fell again into, and was more deeply then before plunged in ſuch ſpiritual deluſions; for now he pretended to have received ſome Revelations and Viſions, which he endevored to manage (as the manner of ſuch is) with fair ſpeeches, and ſeeming Scripture-Goſpel-expreſſions, and pretended to prophecy and foretel things to come: he got acquaintance amongſt ſome of thoſe that deny Ordinances, Scriptures, Chriſt, and are faln from all Goſpel-principles; and, as it ſeems, learned their ways: He then pretended that he could ſpeak with new Tongues, and would babble out words which neither himſelf or others were able to underſtand: and as it is the property of wicked men and ſeducers to wax worſe and worſe, deceiving, and being deceived, ſo hath it been with this man, till at length he hath attained to that height of impiety and blaſphemy, which ſhall be declared in this Relation: By theſe ſpiritual deceits he ſo fell into, was he alſo led into much impiety, as to beat and abuſe his Wife, to deny her to be his Wife, to keep company with other women; for all which evils he was at length, and that very deſervedly, excluded by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation to which he belonged.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:117821:5"/>
            <p>I will now leave <hi>William Frankelin</hi> a little, till having ſaid ſomewhat alſo of his Companion and Partner in wickedneſs, <hi>Mary Gadbury,</hi> I may declare how they came acquainted, and what were the ways of deceit here practiſed by them.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Mary Gadbury</hi> is a married woman, about thirty years of age, her husbands name is <hi>James Gadbury,</hi> who (as her ſelf ſaith) about ſeven years ago forſook her, and with a ſervant he had went away from her into <hi>Holland,</hi> whither (as her ſelf alſo ſaith) ſhe went to him, about five years ſince, but ſtayed very little time with him, ſince that ſhe hath neither ſeen him, or heard from him, but with a daughter ſhe hath lived ever ſince, aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from him in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The place of her living, as ſhe hath declared, hath chiefly been in <hi>Watling</hi> ſtreet in <hi>London,</hi> though, as I have heard, ſhe hath of late much ſhifted her habitation from place to place; her employment hath been to ſell ſmall Wares, as Laces, Pins, Bandſtrings, and other trifles for Gentlewomen. For the manner of her living I have but little on certain grounds to declare: She pretends for her ſelf, that ſhe hath been long time affected to Religion, and to have been a frequent hearer of the Word, of Mr <hi>Sedgwick,</hi> and Mr <hi>Caſe,</hi> in times paſt, but of late chiefly of Mr <hi>J. Goodwin,</hi> and Mr <hi>Jeſſe.</hi> I have ſeen a Petition directed to the Judg of Aſſize in her behalf, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed with the hands of divers men and women, who, as I ſuppoſe, live in or near <hi>Watling</hi> ſtreet, the place of her living, declaring her to have been of honeſt converſation, to have lived in good repute, and religiouſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them: But I have heard others reporting otherwiſe concerning her, as if ſhe had been noted in times paſt to have been of a vicious, lewd, light behaviour: She hath acknowledged concerning her ſelf, that by one of her neighbors ſhe was accuſed before the laſt Lord Major to keep a naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty houſe; but of theſe things concerning her living, I have nothing upon certain information to write, but leave it to others, by farther enquiry at the place of her habitation, to ſatisfie themſelves, if they deſire it, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her.</p>
            <p>And now let me declare how theſe perſons came acquainted, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged together in their ſinful employment and undertaking here in this Country: for this let me acquaint the Reader, That <hi>Mary Gadbury</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been firſt committed to Bridewell, was ſome few days after ſent for thence by the Juſtices, to be committed to the Common-Goal, at which time being examined, ſhe was more free then formerly to declare her ſelf; and beſides what was taken by the Juſtices as her Examination, and might ſerve them for their proceedings in Law with her, ſhe was willing alſo to make farther diſcovery of the Viſions, Revelations and Voyces which ſhe pretended unto, and therein of the way of their acquaintance together,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117821:5"/>the occaſion of their coming together into this County, and the things here done by them, which ſhe did in a Diſcourſe of at leaſt two hours long, and which I, who was then and there preſent, took from her in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, as nigh as might be word for word: This voluntary and free Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of hers I ſhall now make uſe of, as that which will furniſh me with matter to carry on this Relation, faithfully herein reporting the things I then received, and wrote from her, the whole of it in the order ſhe deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered it I ſhall not tranſcribe, for it would be teadious to the Reader ſo to do, and many things therein are very impertinent to ſuch a Relation as this is; but I ſhall ſelect out of it ſuch things as are material, diſpoſing them alſo into ſuch a method as I have propoſed to follow in this Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very.</p>
            <p>Concerning her firſt acquaintance with <hi>William Frankelin,</hi> ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in that her Confeſſion, That it was by means of a woman who lived in the houſe with her, that this woman told her concerning <hi>William Frankelin,</hi> that ſhe having been at his houſe, ſhe ſaw him there embracing a man, whom ſhe called a Devil; but he reproving her for it, ſaid, it was not ſo, but he was one beloved of God: and farther declared to her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning him, that ſhe had ſeen ſuch a man, who had been in ſuch a condition of miſery, as ſhe had never known any to have bin in the like, but one who had deſtroyed his body by ſhooting himſelf, and that from this man, <hi>(viz. William Franklin)</hi> ſhe had heard very ſweet things: Upon this ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired of that woman to bring the man ſhe ſo ſpake of unto her, by whom alſo he was brought unto her: At his firſt coming unto her, he ſpake ſome words which were then dark unto her, but ſome what of God ſhe apprehended ſo ſweet in them, that an Eccho ſounded in her to what he ſaid: At his departing ſhe ſaid to him, <hi>My love is with me;</hi> and he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered to her, <hi>My Peace be with you:</hi> And after that he was departed, and ſhe gone to bed, and waking after her firſt ſleep, ſhe was full of joy and ſinging, ſo was alſo the woman who lay there with her, who had brought this <hi>William Franklin</hi> unto her: This their ſinging was heard by a neighbor, who coming to them ſaid they were Witches. Hitherto the occaſion concerning her firſt acquaintance with <hi>William Franklin,</hi> out of her own Confeſſion.</p>
            <p>What ſo deeply engaged theſe perſons to one another after this their firſt and ſo ſudden acquaintance is next to be diſcovered: Concerning which we will again have recourſe to <hi>Mary Gadburies</hi> Confeſſion, and the Relation ſhe made therein, of ſeveral Viſions, Revelations, Voyces, which ſhe pretended to had and received.</p>
            <p>In that her Confeſſion ſhe declared, that ſhe hath had certain Fits, which ſhe cannot call Convulſion Fits, nor knows how to expreſs them,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117821:6"/>which would ſet her whole body in a trembling, and ſhake the bed where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſhe lay, and continue upon her ſome times from two a clock at night, to ſeven in the morning. Her firſt taking with ſuch a fit was upon a Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day, about twelve a clock at night, which came ſo violently, as it ſet her whole body on trembling, working to her fingers ends, and that ſo ſtrongly, as if ſhe ſhould have been ſtrangled by it, at which time a voyce ſpake forth from her, and ſaid, <hi>It is the Lord, it is the Lord;</hi> but ſhe could not ſay it was her own voyce: At which time clapping her hands together, ſhe had brought to her remembrance a Scripture, which ſhe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard before, as ſhe can remember; <hi>The trees ſhall clap their hands for joy:</hi> Then the voyce that ſpake within her before, ſpake again, <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon is fallen, is fallen:</hi> And then it ſaid further, <hi>There ſhall be no King, but the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords:</hi> And further again, <hi>Rejoyce, O daughters of Sion, break forth into ſinging:</hi> It ſaid alſo, <hi>The Saints ſhall judg the Earth, and the World ſhall confeſs and ſay, This is the City of the Lord:</hi> As alſo, <hi>It ſhall be the deſire of all Nations:</hi> And alſo, <hi>It ſhall be no more called the people of Patience,</hi> (a gathered Church ſo called,) <hi>or the people of Goodwin, but the people of the Lord.</hi> She fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther declared, that ſhe then ſaw ſuch a brightneſs, which ſhe was not able to behold, which for its bigneſs ſeemed half as big as the Moon, when at the full; and though ſhe had laid her ſheet and rug upon her face, ſhe yet ſaw it through all, that ſhe cryed out, ſhe was not able to behold it, it was ſo glorious: There appeared alſo within the curtains of the bed ſo many ſtars, that the curtains ſeemed as full as they could hold with them, that ſhe cryed out, <hi>O the Angels of the Lord!</hi> The which her cry was alſo heard by the woman that lay in the ſame room at her beds feet; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in extremity of pain, ſhe alſo cryed out, <hi>Elo, Elo, My God, why haſt chou forſaken me?</hi> and then the pain left her: After which the Voyce ſpake again unto her as before, <hi>I will not ſo deal with thee again, but as with a Lamb:</hi> and then ſhe lay down, and had a little ſleep, upon her awaking, the ſame voyce ſpake again unto her, as formerly, <hi>I have ſent many a love token to thee, but now thou ſhalt ſee me face to face:</hi> It ſaid alſo, <hi>I will ſend my Son in perſon of a man, who ſhall rule over the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and they ſhall ſee him face to face, eye to eye:</hi> There were alſo Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets ſounding as it were within her, and they had names given them, as of the ſeven Angels, pouring down at every ſound vials of wrath, and at the laſt it was ſaid, <hi>Now the ſeventh Angel ſoundeth.</hi> She declared, that ſhe did not believe to ſee a perſonal Raign of Chriſt, but only ſpiritual in the Soul, till ſhe had heard the voyce ſpeak, as is before mentioned. She further ſaid, that all this which ſhe had thus declared, came to her at ſeveral times. She alſo moreover declared, that after the firſt time <hi>William Franklin</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:117821:6"/>came ſeveral times to her houſe, once in a week or fortnight, and that before he came in at the doors, the voyce before mentioned did ſpeak, <hi>Behold, an Iſraelite, in whom is no guile:</hi> And again, <hi>I have ſpoken to thee in Parables, but now ſpeak no more in Parables, but ſhew thee plainly of the Father.</hi> But that one time eſpecially, <hi>William Franklin</hi> coming to her houſe, (being ſoon after that time that the Voyce ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her, That <hi>the Lord would ſind his Son to raign in the perſon of a man,)</hi> ſhe demanded of him thus: <hi>Hath God revealed to you, that his Son ſhall raign in the perſon of a man?</hi> To which he replyed, <hi>I am the man:</hi> Whereupon ſhe (as laughing at his words) ſaid, That ſhe <hi>looked for the ſame body to come, that ſuffered, and was layed down at the Sepulchre at Jeruſalem:</hi> To which he anſwered, That <hi>that was an old body, but that which he now hath is a new body:</hi> She then told him of his relations, that he was a married man, and had wife and children, which ſhe was ſtartled by: To which he anſwered, That <hi>the body and nature of Franklin, born at Overton, conceived in ſin, and brought forth in iniquity, the Lord had deſtroyed, though the deſtruction thereof were not, as of the body, layd in duſt, viſible to the creature, to be ſeen by it: And as for the woman his wife, he owned her ſo to be his wife, while he carryed about that body, in which he was ſo joyned to her, and he then alſo owned his children to be the children of that body, but now they were no more to him then any other woman and children, and that he had a Command from God to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from her, and that company he before had with her, and that he had not bedded with her as formerly for three years before.</hi> As concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe things thus declared by <hi>William Franklin, Mary Gadbury</hi> acknowledged, in that her Confeſſion, that ſhe had many reaſonings within her ſelf concerning them, and had much ado to entertain them; but at laſt that ſhe did aſſent to it, that it might be, and was ſo, as he had ſaid, and that ſhe was not aſhamed to declare it to be ſo to ſome of her neighbors. Hitherto in this particular from the Confeſſion of <hi>Mary Gadbury:</hi> In which we may perceive <hi>William Franklin</hi> aſſerting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to have a new body, in a ſinful manner renouncing and diſclaiming his relation to his wife and children, and blaſphemouſly declaring himſelf in his Anſwer to the womans Queſtion, to be the Son of God, who ſhould here raign in the perſon of a man, and ſo to be the Chriſt: We have here alſo this fooliſh woman not only hearkening to theſe his Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies, reaſoning and entertaining diſcourſe with him upon them, but very eaſily brought over to give credit unto them; like the woman in the beginning, reaſoning with, and giving credit unto, the Serpent, the Devil, perſwading her husband alſo, as this woman now preſently ſpread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117821:7"/>abroad among her neighbors theſe deluſions wherewith ſhe hath been deceaved. As further teſtimony of the truth of theſe things here declared, I can for my ſelf teſtifie, That ſince the impriſonment of theſe perſons in this City, and that the ſufferings they fell into had ſomewhat broken the ſinful league that was between them, that they began to accuſe each other, for being the cauſe of one anothers troubles, as it is uſual with companions in evil ſo to do, when they are in trouble together, that I, with divers others, heard <hi>Mary Gadbury</hi> relating theſe very things in the preſence and hearing of <hi>William Franklin,</hi> and, as we ſay, to his face, and charging him hereby to have deceived her, and he not able to deny the truth of theſe things ſhe ſo declared concerning him: But queſtionleſs the Voyces ſhe pretends unto to have heard, ſpeaking concerning <hi>Franklin,</hi> when he came unto her, that he was an <hi>Iſraelite, in whom was no guile,</hi> and that now he would ſpeak to her plainly of the Father, and not in Parables (ſhe believing theſe Voyces to be of God, as you will afterward be informed ſhe did) was that which wrought upon her to be ſo eaſily perſwaded to give credit to theſe his Blaſphemies; and by giving credit to them, now to apply to him, as the perſon in whom ſhould be verified, what the Voyce had ſpoken in her, of Gods ſending his Son to raign in the perſon of a man over the Nations, who ſhould ſo ſee him eye to eye, face to face, and ſo to declare of this perſon, as if he were the Chriſt, the Son of God, in whom all this was verified, who was now come to raign upon the Earth in the perſon of a man, even as the Voyce had ſpoken to her.</p>
            <p>After all this <hi>William Franklin,</hi> who before pretending a Command from God, had renounced his wife, and ſeparated from her, doth alſo tell this <hi>Mary Gadbury,</hi> that it was revealed unto him, that ſhe was the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man which was ſet apart for him, as her ſelf alſo declared in her Confeſſion. This alſo, together with the former deceits, was ſo embraced by this ſilly deluded woman, (if I may reckon her herein deluded, and not rather, as I and divers others have jealouſie thereof, and too much ground for it, that all this deceitful buſineſs was, by a compact together, plotted by them, that they might deceive the better,) that ſhe hath the impudence, as to go to <hi>William Franklins</hi> houſe, there of his wife to enquire for him, and to demand of his wife concerning him, whether he were her husband; which the woman affirming, and that ſhe had been ſo many years married to him, and had had divers children by him; this ſtrumpet (for ſo ſhe now becomes) anſwers her, That he was not her husband, nor ſhe his wife, that they were not appointed one for another, ſhe muſt go with thoſe for whom ſhe is appointed, and he with thoſe for whom he is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117821:7"/>meaning, it is like, with her ſelf. This I received from <hi>Franklins</hi> wife, who with tears related this and other paſſages to me.</p>
            <p>Yea further doth this impudent woman proceed, That when <hi>William Franklin</hi> had been one time at her houſe, when he was ready to go away, ſhe perſwades him to abide there that night with her, which he ſaid he would to do her good, ſo that he ſtayed there that night, and lay in the ſame houſe and room, if not in the ſame bed with her, (which I have heard by ſome charged upon her, and ſhe ſcarce able to deny it:) She pretends that ſhe was exceedingly troubled when he was ready to go away, that ſhe was even ready to faint, the cauſe whereof ſhe apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be, that ſhe had ſomething to ſpeak, but could not utter it, yet that ſhe could not be quiet till ſhe had ſpoken it, which was this, of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading him to ſtay all night with her: This I have from her own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion: As alſo, that for this ſhe was accuſed by her neighbors to keep a naughty houſe, and by a Warrant brought before the laſt Lord Major, by whom being examined, ſhe ſaid, that ſhe had no husband but the Lord of Hoſts: She was afterward for this committed to the Counter, from whence after a nights impriſonment ſhe was releaſed upon bail, bound over to anſwer it at <hi>Guild-hall,</hi> where ſhe appeared, but w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>hout any thing done to her was diſmiſt, as ſhe her ſelf related.</p>
            <p>Yea, as a further diſcovery of the ſtrong deluſions whereby this woman is poſſeſſed, doth ſhe pretend to have ſeen the Lord in a Viſion, in the Voyce to bid her ſell what ſhe had, and follow him, which accordingly ſhe did, ſelling all ſhe had, ſave only one bed, but could not be in quiet till ſhe had ſold that likewiſe; with the money ſhe (as ſhe was wiſhed) fed the hungry, and clothed the naked, ſave a ſmall part of it which ſhe kept, and which ſhe ſpent ſhortly after. This I received from the information given me by Mr <hi>Peter Blake</hi> of <hi>Andover,</hi> who demanding of her why ſhe left her profeſſion, gave this in anſwer as the reaſon of it.</p>
            <p>We now ſee theſe two perſons deeply engaged to one another, and the occaſions thereof; the man forſaking his wife and children to accompany himſelf with another woman, and ſhe as much embracing him, and ſelling all to follow him, as her Lord and Chriſt.</p>
            <p>They are now fitted for a march to go forth into ſome Country or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to the ſeducing and deluding of others to follow them in their ways of deſtruction: This County of <hi>Hamp-ſhire</hi> is to be the ſtage, whereon they intend to play the reſt of their parts; but what occaſioned their coming into this County in particular, as well as the things done by them in it, comes now to be declared.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:117821:8"/>
            <p>What ever is undertaken by theſe perſons, ſomething of ſome Viſions, Revelations, or Voyces muſt be pretended as the ground of it, and the better to deceive others thereby. This County of <hi>Southampton</hi> would ſeem of all other the moſt unfit to be choſen by them, to carry on their deſign in it; <hi>William Franklin</hi> being this Country-man, born and bred at <hi>Overton,</hi> a town in it, as I have before declared; ſo that he could not in this Country be long hid, and his Condition, and relation to his Wife &amp; Children being at the place of his birth well known, it could not but be a very great ſcandal to their way, his forſaking them, and accompanying with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther woman: This having been by ſome put to them, and their folly cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured in it, the Viſions and Revelations ſeen by them have been alledged as the Reaſon of it. Hear we then what <hi>Mary Gadbury</hi> hath related in her ſo large Confeſsion, ſeveral times before already mentioned in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to this particular alſo.</p>
            <p>She declared that ſhe ſaw in Viſion a perfect man, as in the Clouds, with clothing on, and a ſharp ſword in his hand: She ſaw him taking down a Childe, and ſetting it as in a Church, or Congregation, in the midſt of the People; and the Childe was ſo beautiful that ſhe had never ſeen the like. She then looked for the man, but could ſee no more of him at that time, but onely the hair of his head. But another time ſhe ſaw the ſame man again in Viſion, running ſo faſt, that ſhe had never ſeen the like; and it was revealed to her as the meaning thereof, that he made haſte, and it was full time. She alſo ſaw the ſame man again in another Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, coming from off the top of an houſe, and flying towards this Country; and the Country was named to her to be an hill Country, the Land of <hi>Ham,</hi> which ſhe underſtood to be this Country of <hi>Hampſhire,</hi> and it was ſo revealed unto her to be, by the like voyce that had ſo ſeveral times ſpoken before unto her. When ſhe ſaw the man ſo flying, a Lamb alſo flew after him as cloſe as might be, and ſhe ſaw the wool of the Lamb upon the back of it; and the Voyce ſpake in her, and ſaid concerning it, <hi>This is the Bride, the Lambs Wife, the Church of the living God.</hi> All this was ſeen by her, but very little before ſhe came with <hi>William-Franklin</hi> into this County: And as ſoon as ſhe had ſeen this Viſion, ſhe took occaſion to declare it to <hi>William Franklin,</hi> and he declared, that it had been alſo revealed to him to go into the hill Country, the Land of <hi>Ham:</hi> And now it was (as appears by the circumſtances of her Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) that <hi>William Franklin</hi> told her, that it had been revealed to him, that ſhe was the woman who was ſet apart for him. The conſtruction made by both of them of all this, was, That by the Viſion which ſhe had ſeen, and the Revelation which he had, both ſo anſwering to one another,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117821:8"/>they were warned to go together into that Country of <hi>Hampſhire.</hi> This Viſion hath been declared by her to be a Heavenly Viſion, which ſhe judged ſhe might in no wiſe be diſobedient unto. And this ſhe declared to be the Reaſon that brought them down into this Country; and hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reſolved upon their journey but two nights before they undertook it, the Voyce that had ſpake to her at firſt, and ſo all along in the ſeveral Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, ſaid then alſo unto her, <hi>I have made an end of ſin &amp; tranſgreſſion for me and my people:</hi> And afterward, at another time, it ſaid, <hi>Awake, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake, ye that ſleep; put on your beautiful garments, O Daughters of Sion; for the marriage of the Lamb is come.</hi> Upon all this ſhe came down into this County, which otherwiſe ſhe was very loath to do; that though ſickneſs which ſhe had, and for her health ſake, as alſo to avoyd the trouble and clamours of <hi>Franklins</hi> wife, made her willing to leave the City, and come into the Country; yet theſe things ſo revealed in theſe Viſions and Voyces to her, was the Reaſon of their choyce of, and comming into this Country. Hitherto you have in all this the words of <hi>Mary Gadburies</hi> own Confeſſion, as nigh as may be.</p>
            <p>By theſe Viſions thus occaſioning their coming into this Country, we ſee, Firſt. The <hi>Scripture</hi> abuſed in this particular; the Land of <hi>Ham.</hi> muſt be with them <hi>Hampſhire:</hi> From the Scripture is this expreſsion of the Land of <hi>Ham</hi> borrowed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.23. <hi>&amp; Pſa.</hi> 106.22. The Holy Ghoſt thereby meaning the Land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> as the Text it ſelf expounds it; <hi>Iſrael alſo came into Egypt; and Jacob ſojourned in the Land of Ham:</hi> and that Land of <hi>Egypt</hi> was ſo called the Land of <hi>Ham,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by <hi>Hams</hi> poſterity it was repleniſhed with people, and inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited: The name of that Country is in the Original <hi>Miſraim,</hi> who was one of <hi>Hams</hi> ſons, by whom that Country was peopled: But this County of <hi>Southamptou,</hi> vulgarly called <hi>Hampſhire,</hi> muſt be the Land of <hi>Ham</hi> with them, becauſe the firſt ſillable of it is <hi>Ham.</hi> Thus doth the Devil in theſe Viſions teach them to abuſe Scripture. Secondly, It appears, by the conſtruction theſe perſons made of theſe Viſions, that they applyed it wholly to themſelves, That <hi>Franklin</hi> was the running flying man, and <hi>Mary Gadbury</hi> muſt be the Lamb flying cloſe after him; How elſe could their ſo flying towards ſuch a Country be a warning and direction to them in Viſion to go into that Country? Hereby it came to paſs, that as the former Viſions had declared <hi>William Franklin</hi> to be <hi>the Chriſt;</hi> ſo by this which the Voyce is ſaid to ſpeak of the Lamb, by this woman, applied to her ſelf, ſhe becomes the Bride, his wife. Hence it was I ſuppoſe, that as he was proclamed by her to be <hi>the Christ,</hi> ſo ſhe declared of her ſelf, and was acknowledged by their ſeduced Followers,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117821:9"/>to be <hi>the Spouſe of Chriſt;</hi> and ſhe blaſphemouſly to apply to her ſelf the <hi>Scripture</hi> of the <hi>Lambs marriage being come, and his Bride to have made her ſelf ready,</hi> which ſhe pretends by her Voyce to have been ſpoken to her. Thus is <hi>Franklin</hi> now in the room of Chriſt to her, he taking to himſelf what is proper to Chriſt; and ſhe putting her ſelf in the room of the Church, Chriſts myſtical body, to be <hi>the Spouſe of Christ, the Bride, the Lambs wife.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By what hath been before declared, we finde theſe perſons with their mindes fraught with all manner of the higheſt Blaſphemies, reſolved up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a journey into this County of <hi>Southampton,</hi> whither by their Viſions they pretend to have been directed. According to this their Reſolution in <hi>November</hi> laſt, <hi>Anno</hi> 1649. they undertake this their reſolved jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney: and all that hitherto hath been related of the Tranſactions of theſe perſons and dealings of them, towards one another, was much within the compaſs of a quarter of a year (as nigh as by any circumſtances I can gueſs) from the time of their firſt acquaintance, to their undertaking of this journey. At this time here mentioned, <hi>William Franklin</hi> forſaking his Wife, Children, Calling, Employment, Family, and taking <hi>Mary Gadbury</hi> unto him, aſſociating himſelf with her, as if his wife, (but indeed rather to ſay the leaſt, his Concubine,) and ſhe alſo (notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her knowledg that he had a Wife and Children, and her ſelf alſo, for ought ſhe knew to the contrary, a married woman, and her Husband living) doth yet joyn her ſelf unto him, as his Companion in wickedneſs, and both together came from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Andover,</hi> a Town in this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Southampton,</hi> in the Wagon that weekly travelleth between theſe places. Thus while the written Word of God chargeth every man that hath a Family <hi>to live in and with it, to provide for it, and reckons him worſe then an Infidel that doth not ſo do; and warneth all to fly fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and all ſuch uncleanneſs, and whatſoever hath the appearance of evil in it, in respect of that or other ſins:</hi> Yet can theſe perſons by their Viſions and Revelations finde pretences to caſt off all their Relations, and the Duties of them, and in ſuch a way (that cannot by any that knows it, or ſhall read this relation of it, but be cenſured for fleſhly unncleanneſs) aſſociate themſelves unto, and keep company with one another; to ſuch a height of imprety are they already grown, and that through the juſt Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, having forſaken his Word, and giving heed to ſuch Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Revelations, and Voyces, whereof not God, but the Devil, muſt be judged the Author, they being ſo contrary to God and his Word; if yet there were indeed any ſuch Viſions, and were not things bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deviſed by them, the better to deceive one another, and others by them.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:117821:9"/>
            <p>Being come to <hi>Andover,</hi> they take up their lodging at the ſign of the Starre, which Inne is kept by one <hi>Michael Rutlie,</hi> who to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with his wife, have been well eſteemed for the profeſſion of Religion, and after ſome acquaintance of theſe perſons with this man and his wife, they could pretend to them that in ſome viſion they had ſeen both of them, and that in ſome revelation it had been made knowne to them, that there ſhould be their lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; while they were there, which was about the ſpace of a moneth, in all the time of it that they were there together, they kept company one with another, and as husband and wife they lay in the ſame bed together: The Sabbath day after their arrivall at Andover, <hi>VVilliam Frankelin</hi> (as I have heard) offered to preach in the publike place there, but that being denied him, he would yet preſume to do it in the Inne where he lay, which alſo he did ſeverall times while he was there, divers reſorting thither to hear him; he ſtayed not long there, but he returned up to London, to ſupply himſelf with money, but with a promiſe to return againe in a fortnight, and at his return to take a houſe for their living in Overton, where ſhe ſhould be placed and abide, and where he would ſupply her with maintenance, though he himſelf by reaſon of his trade, muſt be forced to be ſomtime from her at London: While <hi>VVilliam Franklin</hi> was at Andover, (before his journey up to London) they contained themſelves from ſpreading their blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies, ſuppoſing that it would not be ſeaſonable ſo ſoon to do it, till he by his preaching and diſcourſe might ſomwhat have inſinuated himſelfe into the minds of people apt to be deceived, which having a very plauſible and affected (though ſlow) manner of ſpeech, delivering things in language that people were not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily able to underſtand, having a ſeeming ſhew of ſpirituality in it, he ſoon deceived many people, making them to admire the things they underſtood not; but he having herein by preaching acted his part firſt, the reſt is to be done by her in his abſence, as <hi>Mahomets</hi> wife tels among her Goſſips, that her husband was a Prophet, and ſo firſt ſpread abroad the fame of that falſe Prophet; ſo muſt the quean in her deceitfull companions abſence, tell abroad that ſhe had ſeen Chriſt in the perſon of a man, not declaring him to be the perſon at preſent whom ſhe did thereby intend, that ſo by the time he ſhould returne, it would ſomwhat appear how their deſign would take, and what might be like to be the effect of it: Thus have they plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their buſineſſe, and each hath their part to act in it, as they are moſt fitted for it.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:117821:10"/>
            <p>As ſoon therefore as <hi>VVilliam Franklin</hi> was departed, and was upon his journey towards London, <hi>Mary Gadbury</hi> now by his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture left alone to act her part by her ſelf, doth preſently begin to ſpread it abroad, that ſhe had ſeen Chriſt in the perſon of a man; and that the rumour of this might the better ſpead it ſelf abroad, ſhe took all opportunities for the divulging of it: This report therefore of hers being not in a cold manner delivered, but with much earneſtneſſe inſiſted upon, perſiſted in, and preſſed by her, as that which by no arguments of any whatſoever ſhe would be beat off from, did ſo on ſpread it ſelfe amongſt the people by reaſon of the ſtrangeneſſe of it, and by reaſon of the reſort to that place, being a conſiderable Market-town, and the houſe wherein ſhe lay an Inn, and place of great entertainment; the whole Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey was alſo from thence preſently filled with the rumor of it; And now do multitudes of perſons both of that Town, and alſo of the Countrey, reſort to her lodging to viſit and to ſpeak with her, the perſon of whom ſuch ſtrange things have been heard by them, and generally all the diſcourſe with her is concerning what ſhe had ſo aſſerted of her ſeeing of Chriſt in the perſon of a man: Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this her report, ſome labour by queſtions to ſearch further into it, and try what further diſcovery can be had from her concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it, divers queſtions therefore are propoſed to her concerning the perſon, in ſeeing of whom ſhe ſo aſſerted that ſhe had ſeen Chriſt, as what manner of perſon he was, his ſhape and forme, to obtain from her ſome deſcription of it, what ſhould be the end of his coming, where ſhould be his preſent abode, what ſhould be ſpoken by him at his firſt appearance to her, and by what occaſion ſhe firſt came to the ſight of him.</p>
            <p>Company thus coming to her, thus alſo reaſoning and queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with her, where ſhe ſaw any ſet to oppoſe her, and able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover her deceits and blaſphemies, very ſly would ſhe be in diſclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing any thing to them, or in their preſence, and would uſually de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare at ſuch times that ſhe was not then free to ſpeak; yea, in her own large confeſſion (out of which I have already related ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things) ſhe declared, that when ſome came to oppoſe her, it, was given her to diſcerne it, and that the voice that all along had ſpoken to her ſhould then alſo ſpeak to her, and ſay, <hi>Seal up the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> and that this was the cauſe of her ſilence to them, and unto thoſe who would eſpecially with any zeale declare againſt the things ſhe aſſerted, and againſt her alſo for her blaſphemies, ſhe would uſually give ſome reproachfull language, calling them Satan,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117821:10"/>or ſome ſuch names; and when ſhe would ſpeak moſt moderately to them, it would be to tell them, that their <hi>eyes were not yet open, the time would come when their eyes ſhould be opened, and they ſhould then ſee what ſhe had now told them:</hi> But where ſhe ſaw any perſons though but ſeemingly to comply with her, (for ſo by a ſeeming com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance deceiving her, ſome got theſe things from her, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they ſhould not have heard) or any that were weak in under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, not able to diſcerne and diſcover her deceits and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies, or any that ſhe ſaw were credulous, ready to be ſhaken, ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily to be wrought upon by her, to theſe ſhe would freely ſpeak and deliver her ſelf, and uſe all means to win upon them to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing of them: Something alſo hath been gotten from her in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the ſeverall Quaeres before mentioned, wherein ſhe would declare many things of her viſions and revelations anſwerable to what hath been from her own confeſſion before related, eſpecially upon declaring of the occaſion of her ſight of him whom ſhe called the <hi>Chriſt;</hi> ſuch a deſcription would ſhe alſo give of his perſon, to be a plaine man in gray cloaths, that ſhe knew the place of his living in London, how gloriouſly he at firſt appeared, that ſhe could not behold his glory, but deſired his coming to her in a plainer form, and that in a fortnight he would come downe thither to Ando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to her; and many ſuch things ſhe declared in the deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him, which ſo well agreed to <hi>VVilliam Franklin,</hi> who had been with her, and was now gone to London, promiſing her in a fortnight to returne, that many preſently deemed that he was the perſon in all this held out by her to be the <hi>Chriſt;</hi> the end of his coming ſhe would declare to be to reigne upon the earth, to erect and ſet up his Kingdome, and for what he ſhould ſpeak to her, that he had never honoured a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny woman in ſo appearing to her, as he now did honour her in this his appearance to her.</p>
            <p>Theſe, and many ſuch like, were the things declared by her in the conferences ſhe had with ſundry perſons, in anſwer to the queſtions by them propoſed to her, many blaſphemous expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons did now alſo at ſundry times fall from her in relation to her ſelfe, as if ſhe were the Bride, the Lambs wife, yea, and did take it no robbery to be equall to God; the Scripture, when in any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference alledged to her, was generally flighted by her, the greateſt Authorities ſhe alledged was her owne viſions and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations, many of which were yet in Scripture-expreſſions de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:117821:11"/>by her, that ſhe might deceive the better by them: And it is a wonder to conſider that any perſon ſhould be not ſo much weak, as ſottiſh, to believe thoſe ſo manifeſt, palpable, groſſe deluſions, and blaſphemies, as were thus vented by this deceitfull woman, yet ſo it was, that many both in Town and Countrey were ſome ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, ſome wholly ſeduced by theſe her deceits.</p>
            <p>It would be tedious to the Reader, and that which would cauſe this Relation (wherein I deſire, and ſhall indeavour all poſſible bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity) quickly to ſwell into a conſiderable volume, ſhould I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to relate what was declared by this blaſphemous woman: (while ſhe was thus by her ſelfe at Andover venting her blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies) in the ſeverall conferences between her, and ſundry particular perſons who came to ſee her, and to have (and had) diſcourſe with her.</p>
            <p>It ſhall therefore content me (and I hope it will my Reader al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo) to declare what paſſed between this ſeducing woman, and thoſe that being ſeduced by her, did hearken to her, and follow her in theſe her waies of deceit, and blaſphemie, and the way and courſe taken by her, which by the permiſſion of God, and through the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacy of Satan, was effectuall to the ſeducing of them: That large confeſſion of <hi>Mary Gadburies</hi> ſo oftentimes before mentioned, I ſhall now again have recourſe unto, and make uſe of it, as that which will ſufficiently furniſh me with matter to carry on this part of my relation.</p>
            <p>In that her confeſſion ſhe declared, that while ſhe was at the Star in Andover, (while as yet <hi>William Franklin</hi> was with her, and not gone upon his journey towards London, as is before related) ſhe was one night ſo taken as a woman in travail, and with ſuch paines ſo coming and going, as throes of a woman in that condition; but that the paines ſhe now indured were more painfull then thoſe of women in that condition, which ſhe could well tell, having had the experience of both: At which time of her paine, the ſame voice mentioned before to have ſpoken to her in the former viſions, ſpake this now again, <hi>Shall I bring to the birth, and not give ſtrength to bring forth?</hi> All that night (wherein theſe pains and this voice came thus unto her) ſhe was very ill with them, and all the day following alſo, which was the Sabbath day, wherein divers came to hear <hi>VVilliam Franklin</hi> ſpeak ſomwhat unto them; the day after being Munday, <hi>VV.F.</hi> went to London, after whoſe departure ſhe began to declare, that ſhe had ſeen the Lord Chriſt <hi>in the perſon of a man,</hi> and this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117821:11"/>others ſhe declared in particular to Mr. <hi>Woodward,</hi> which Mr. <hi>Woodward</hi> was then Miniſter of Crooxeaſton, a village ſome few miles diſtant from that town of Andover, and to <hi>Edward Spradbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> which <hi>Edward Spradbury</hi> is by his profeſſion a Clothworker li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in Andover, and to him ſhe alſo declared, concerning the pains before mentioned then continuing upon her, how great they were, and that ſhe ſhould never have reſt till ſhe were delivered of what ſhe travailed withall: Thus farre already her confeſſion: But before I go further in it, it will be neceſſary I give ſome informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to my Reader which may ſerve to clear his underſtanding ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what, concerning what here already is, and what further is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to him.</p>
            <p>The Reader is therefore here to underſtand, that theſe pains and travails which this deceitfull woman doth thus pretend unto (if any ſuch paines there were, and that theſe were not things altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the feigned by her) ſhe pretends alſo to be of God, and to be for ſome ſpirituall, and not for any naturall birth, and ſhe ſeems to take ground for this from the ſpeech of the forementioned voice unto her concerning it; but how wickedly and blaſphemouſly that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Lord by his Prophet concerning Sion his Church, and concerning the birth of Chriſt, the man-child, and of all his people, raiſed and borne together, vertually with and in him in his Reſurrection, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 66.7, 8, 9. according to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. he hath quickned us and raiſed us together with Chriſt, is here I ſay, ſinfully, wickedly, blaſphemouſly applied, and aſſumed by this blaſphemous creature to her ſelfe, making her ſelfe thereby to be the Sion there mentioned: But ſtrange it cannot be thought, that having ſet up this <hi>W. F.</hi> to be the Chriſt, and applying to him what is proper to Chriſt, and her ſelfe to be the Bride, the Lambs wife, the Spouſe of Chriſt, ſhe ſhould now thus apply and aſſume to her ſelf what concerning Sion and the true myſticall Spouſe and Church of Chriſt is delivered in the Scripture.</p>
            <p>Here alſo is further to be knowne, that this fooliſh woman was uſually wont, as wickedly to apply to her ſelſe in theſe her falſly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended travails that ſpeech of the Apoſtle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.19. ſaying in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall that ſhe did travail in birth till Chriſt were formed in them, to thoſe with whom ſhe conferred, and in particular when ſhe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived any one like to be wrought upon, and ſeduced by her, then would ſhe pretend her travail to be for ſuch a one, who being at length wholly wrought upon and ſeduced by her, it muſt be aſcribed to her
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:117821:12"/>travails, as an effect of them, that muſt be the perſon for whom ſhe was in travail, and ſuch a perſon the ſpirituall birth now brought forth by her; according to this is that which ſhe hath thus declared of her paines and travells to be underſtood by us: But one thing I may not omit here fit to be inſerted, evidenced by a Conſtable, when the buſineſſe concerning the pretended travails of this wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and her ſpirituall birth was examined and heard before the Judge of Aſſize, <hi>viz.</hi> that he heard from <hi>Edward Spradbury</hi> that this woman had been in travail, and was delivered; and asking of what ſhe had been delivered, it was anſwered, of a Dragon, and what ſhe was ſo delivered of, her Lord and Chriſt had ſlain it on the bed:—Hence I ſuppoſe it was, that ſo ſtrong a report was ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time raiſed and carried about the Countrey, as if this woman had been in ſome reall travail, and had been indeed delivered of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, or ſome ſuch monſtrous birth.</p>
            <p>But let us now return to the courſe of our Relation, and for the carrying of it on, have recourſe againe to the large confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that woman, declaring therein her dealing with ſundry parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular perſons, and the ſeducing of them, <hi>Edward Spradbury</hi> is the firſt that (by any circumſtance I can find) was ſeduced by her, and gave credit to her blaſphemies; and though I cannot learne by what meanes he was wrought upon by her, yet I perceive he ſtuck not long at the buſineſſe, but was quickly perſwaded to follow her in her deceits, to believe according to what ſhe had aſſerted, <hi>VVil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Franklin</hi> to be the <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and with many blaſphemous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions to declare him ſo to be unto others alſo, and to ſerve this woman as a very active inſtrument for ſeducing of other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; for thus it followes in the Confeſſion, That <hi>Edward Sprad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> riding that way went to M. <hi>VVodwards</hi> at Crooxeaſon, and there told Mr. <hi>VVoodward's</hi> wife what he had heard this woman to ſay, <hi>viz.</hi> of her having ſeen Chriſt in the perſon of a man; but that Mrs. <hi>VVoodward</hi> not induring to hear of it, ſaid, I do think it is a Devil, but that a few daies afterwards Mrs. <hi>VVoodward</hi> [as ſhe did her ſelf declare and acknowledge] had it in a viſion revealed to her, that this Mrs. <hi>Gadbury</hi> was the woman in the Revelation, <hi>clothed with the Sun, and the Moon under her feet, and there travailing in paine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She moreover declared in this her confeſſion, that in the time of <hi>W. Franklins</hi> abſence at London, ſhe could not take her reſt one night in the week, ſhe would very willingly have ſlept in the day, but that the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117821:12"/>voice ſaid to her, <hi>thou ſhalt take no reſt til I have accompliſhed my work;</hi> and it ſaid moreover, <hi>ſhe is coming, ſhe is coming:</hi> Of whom the voice thus ſpake, ſhe declared ſhe could not tell; but ſuppoſed it to be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of a woman in Wells, named <hi>Joan Garment,</hi> whom ſhe had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſeen outwardly, but ſhe had ſeen her in viſion;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Thus can theſe deceitfull per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, though</hi> 100. <hi>miles di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, ſee one another in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Joan Garment,</hi> had alſo ſeen her in viſion, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared concerning her, <hi>That there was a woman in London, ſet apart of God for a great work, and to be one of the Sealed, but is therein mistaken, as appears by what followes:</hi> Of this <hi>Joan Garment</hi> ſhe thought the voice to have ſpoken, but ſhortly after Mrs. <hi>Woodward</hi> came; at whoſe coming ſhe that had before been very ſilent (the voice having bid her to ſeal up the viſion) was now very free in ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and rejoyced exceedingly, and was not able to conceal her joy, or contain her ſelf from tears, although ſhe did much endeavour it, knowing that Mrs. <hi>Woodward</hi> had ſomething revealed to her, though what it was, was as yet not unto her ſelf revealed. But now Mrs. <hi>Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> being come, ſhe declared, that it had been revealed to her, that the glory of God ſhould be ſeen in her, (meaning this M. <hi>Gadbury</hi>) and that ſhe had evill thoughts of her,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Now alſo I ſuppoſe it was Mrs.</hi> W. <hi>related her foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned viſion.</hi>
               </note> but it had been thus revealed to her; <hi>do not have ſuch thoughts, for thou peirceſt her, thou woundest her.</hi> That night there ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped together with this <hi>Mary Gadbury</hi> in her cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, Mr. <hi>Woodward</hi> and his wife, and <hi>Edward Spradbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> At the end of their ſupper, though ſhe was very well, yet ſhe felt on a ſuddain ſomething riſing in her like to ſtop her breath, which made her to cry out; and they all that were with her came, and ſome held her head, ſome her back; at laſt ſhe cried to them to be unlaced with ſpeed, or to have her laces cut; which being done, ſhe yet thought, ſhe ſhould have died with extremity of pain, her pains were like to womens throes going and coming; and after the great pain was over, a laughter aroſe in her for the abundance of glory which ſhe ſaw; the voice ſpake in her, though not ſo audibly as for others to hear it, <hi>Who hath beleeved our report,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Scripture most blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</note> 
               <hi>and to whom is the arm of the Lord revealed?</hi> and ſhe her ſelf ſpake out theſe words; <hi>ſo ſuddain as you ſee this change, ſo ſuddainly will the Lord appear to all.</hi> Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Mrs. <hi>Woodward</hi> ſaid, by what I now ſee I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve with more confidence then before. How alſo doth Mrs. <hi>Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> invite the woman to go to her houſe with her the next day, by
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:117821:13"/>reaſon the people of the Starre were unnaturall to her, and ſhe her ſelf was alſo directed by a command, the voice ſpeaking, <hi>go with her;</hi> but it had not ſo much power in it, as to make her go preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, onely it was revealed to her, and ſhe declared it to Mrs. <hi>Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> that though ſhe went not her ſelf, yet the viſion ſhe had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeen of the woman in travaile, ſhould again be with her: up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Mrs. <hi>Woodward</hi> the next day went home: Thus farre her confeſſion for this, of what paſſed between her and Mrs. <hi>Woodward,</hi> whereby we ſee this Mrs. <hi>W.</hi> wholly perverted, even renouncing her faith in Chriſt, giving up her ſelfe to this deceiver, and together with <hi>Edward Spradbury</hi> become the proſelites of this ſeducing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull Strumpet.</p>
            <p>We have ſeen how well this <hi>M. Gadbury</hi> hath acted her part, and it is now time to inquire after <hi>W. Franklin,</hi> he (as hath been before related) going to London with a promiſe of returning in a fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, was as good as his word, and did returne according to the time appointed, upon Saturday the 8. of December, and being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, he declared to this woman, (as her ſelf hath expreſſed in her confeſſion) that he was bid by a voice that ſpake to him, to make haſt, and come away, and was by it informed and made ſenſible of her condition at the Star, and how unnaturall and unkind the people of that place were unto her; for ſo it was that by this time of <hi>Franklin</hi>'s return, it was ſufficiently divulged and knowne about the town, that theſe perſons were not husband and wife, as it was before ſuppoſed, but that he had forſaken his wife and children to keep company with this woman, and ſhe alſo to be a married wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; information hereof came ſundry waies to this town, as from Overton, not farre thence, the place of <hi>W. Franklins</hi> birth and breeding, where himſelfe, his condition, and his relations were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well knowne; and alſo from <hi>London,</hi> where <hi>W. Franklins</hi> wife ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving underſtood her husband and this woman in the Andover wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon to be gone together into that Countrey, did inquire out Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Hunt</hi> the Waggoner, and inquiring after her husband, did with many tears make unto him a moſt ſad complaint, and dolefull Iamentation, for her husbands ſo forſaking of her, and leaving her thereby in ſo miſerable a condition, that ſhe had no means of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence, but that ſhe wanted bread for her ſelfe and her children: This report from <hi>W. Franklins</hi> wife was by <hi>Hunt</hi> the Waggoner, upon his return brought down to Andover, and was a great means to make theſe perſons grow very odious in that place: And now
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:117821:13"/>was this by divers objected to <hi>M. Gadbury</hi> (ſometime before <hi>W. Frankelins</hi> return) how, or with what pretence ſhe could or durſt to keep company with ſuch a man, whom ſhe knew to be another womans husband, and in accompanying with her to forſake his wife and children; and was likewiſe charged upon both of them together at his return; unto which ſhe would anſwer; that <hi>W. Fr.</hi> had no wife after the fleſh but ſhe, nor had ſhe any other husband after the fleſh but he; that it's poſſible a woman and children might ſo lay claim to him, who yet were no wife and children of his; he having a new body and nature, they were dead to him, and he to them; that ſhe looked upon this as but the ſcandall of the world.</p>
            <p>However this ſo great a ſcandall they were not able to wipe off ſo eaſily, but that it had deep impreſſion on divers to render theſe perſons odious unto them; yea <hi>Michael Rutlie</hi> and his wife, their hoſt and hoſteſſe, who kept the ſtar, and with whom they lodged, now began to grow ſtrange, and as they reckoned it, unnaturall and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind to them; inſomuch that <hi>W. Fr.</hi> returning the Saturday, on the Munday and Tueſday following, both he and his companion having this of their ſinfull practiſe by Mr. <hi>Rutlie</hi> related to them, who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured alſo to declare to them from the word of God, which they little regarded how ſinfull it was; they were warned by him to depart, and with all ſpeed that might be to be gone out of his houſe: at which time of their being thus warned to depart, divers ſtrange and blaſphemous expreſſions came from <hi>W. Frankelin,</hi> ſaying, <hi>That he knew his Maker, and his Maker knew him, and he was one with his Maker:</hi> and now they charged Mr. <hi>Rutlie,</hi> as if he were another <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late,</hi> thus perſecuting of them, thus receiving the ſcandall of the world againſt them.</p>
            <p>There being now no longer abode for them at <hi>Andover,</hi> and <hi>M. Gadbury</hi> having told this <hi>W. Frankelin</hi> upon his returne of Mrs. <hi>Woodwards</hi> invitation; it is now very acceptable to them, and they bethink themſelves of accepting of it, and going thither; according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on Tueſday December 11. departing from Andover they arrive at Crooxeaſon, where they are very welcome to Mr. <hi>VVoodward</hi> and his wife, &amp; have their entertainment there in his houſe for about the ſpace of ſix weeks, til by the Juſtices Warrants they were ſought after, and apprehended, as you will afterwards underſtand. Mrs. <hi>VVoodward</hi> [as <hi>M.G.</hi> hath confeſſed] had been told concerning the wife and children of <hi>VV. F.</hi> but ſhe did not then regard it, looking now upon the principle of God in the creature, &amp; what had been revealed to her.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117821:14"/>Thus with theſe perſons, it is nothing to lay aſide naturall relation and affection, to deſert, yea to run away from wife and children, yea in an adulterous way to keep company together, and to lie with one another, if ſomething of a Viſion or Revelation may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended; though herein be enough to diſcover ſuch viſions and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations to be of the Devil, and not of God, when occaſion ſhall be given by them, and encouragement alſo to perſons, to walk in ſuch ſinfull practiſes ſo manifeſtly contrary to the Word and Will of God. Being now ſetled in their freſh quarters at Crooxeaſon, where they are ſure to have free quarter; having made ſo good an exchange, by removing from an Inne to a private (and that a Miniſters) houſe; being I ſay here ſetled, <hi>VV. Frankelin</hi> declares, that it is revealed to him, that this place where they now were is the wilderneſſe appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the nouriſhing of the woman, a time, times and half a time: here he ſtaied a moneth, and after that went again upon another journie to London: And now, what was done at this place, and what viſions, revelations, voices, this M. <hi>Gad.</hi> pretends at this place to have received alſo, I ſhall make ſome diſcovery of from her own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</p>
            <p>She declared in her confeſſion, that one night of her being at Crooxeaſon, awaking after her firſt ſleep, ſhe felt a weight upon her breaſt, as if it had been a ſtone of a load weight; and ſhe ſaid,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The former travail brought forth Mrs.</hi> Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; <hi>and this ſeemes to be another tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther birth.</hi>
               </note> O Lord when ſhall I be releaſed of this miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? at laſt the Voice ſpake unto her, and what it ſpake was chiefly concerning two men, living near Ando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, the name of the one being <hi>Rutlie,</hi> the other <hi>Bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,</hi> and alſo of a woman whoſe name is <hi>VVaterman;</hi> theſe perſons had much exclaimed againſt <hi>Frankelin</hi> and her, for that he having a wife and three children ſhould keep company with another woman, and for ſaying that he was the Chriſt. The Voice naming theſe perſons, ſaid of them, <hi>They have a godly zeal in them, they love what thou loveſt, they ſpeak not againſt my glory, but against the old nature which is gone; they ſee no farther then that; the Voice alſo hid her by</hi> M Woodward <hi>to ſend for</hi> Rutlie <hi>and</hi> Bunnie, &amp; it ſaid of them, <hi>they ſhal be pure they ſhal ſee me:</hi> then the Voice ſpake forth aloud,
<note place="margin">This ſhe ſaid was ſpoken with ſuch violence in her, that ſhe feared ſhe ſhould have been ſtrangled with the force of it.</note> as the voice of a man roaring out in ſpeaking, <hi>I am the Lord of Hoſts,</hi> JEHOVAH <hi>is my name, the high and holy one; I am of a pure eye, a God that cannot behold iniquity; I will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veil
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:117821:14"/>my ſelfe now, and they ſhall ſee me face to face, eye to eye. It is no more the morning-ſtar, but the great day of the Lord is come.</hi> Then the Voice ſpake directly to, and of her ſelf ſaying, <hi>Thou ſhalt be clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in a white robe which I will give thee, and they ſhall all ſee thy whiteneſſe, for I have made thee pure;</hi>
               <note place="margin">O groſſe pride, deceit and hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie!</note> 
               <hi>as it is all pure within, ſo ſhall it be without; thou ſhalt be clothed all in white, a reſemblance of the inward purity, and I will make thee to be as a Phenix.</hi> Then the Voice com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded her to ſpeak for a thing that was in the houſe, (which was ſome white linnen cloth) and to make her a white robe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, which ſhould ſerve onely for the preſent, for ſhe ſhould afterward be covered all over with white: She told Mrs. <hi>VVoodward</hi> what the Voice had ſaid concerning the white cloth, but Mrs. <hi>W.</hi> told her that ſhe would ſpeak to her husband to buy ſome Holland of ſeven groats an ell, to ſerve for that uſe, whereby it ſeems Mrs. <hi>VVoodward,</hi> was not willing to be ſo eaſily cheated of her white cloth. With this anſwer, this M. <hi>Gadbury</hi> was much troubled, yet ſhe thought to ſpeak no more for it: but <hi>Mrs. W.</hi> being gone forth, the Voice ſaid again to her, <hi>Doth ſhe think that wil ſuffice? the beſt things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to thee:</hi> but <hi>M. Gad.</hi> declaring her ſelf loth to trouble her, the Voice ſaid, <hi>If ſhe be offended, I will pacifie the offence;</hi> then ſhe called Mrs. <hi>Woodward</hi> again, and asked her, if ſhe thought any thing too good for the Lord: who anſwered, no; and ſo at length both her ſelf and her husband gave their conſent to part with the linnen cloth to her, for the uſe ſhe deſired. Thus by a fine trick of cleanly convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, is Mrs. <hi>W.</hi> cheated out of her white cloth, and <hi>M. G.</hi> by this Artificiall way of deceitfull cheating and jugling, hath got her a good piece of cloth, and accordingly makes her an outer-garment with it, that it might ſhew forth her inward purity: ſhe now ſeeth, that if ſhe hath a mind to any thing which any of her proſelites hath, it is but to pretend a Voice or Viſion for it, and it muſt preſently be given to her.</p>
            <p>But to return to her confeſſion, wherein ſhe farther declared, that one night being broad awake, ſhe ſaw a white foot, which the Voice commanded to reſt upon her,
<note place="margin">Which I ſuppoſe to be the ſame night wherein ſhe had the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer viſion.</note> and to her ſight the foot was ſet upon her ſhoulders; and ſhe ſaw no more of it: at which time all within the curtains of her bed was a great brightneſſe, by a multitude of ſtars, that exceeded the morning
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:117821:15"/>ſtar in brightneſſe: At that morning the Voice ſpake aloud in her, <hi>Ariſe, ariſe, all ye that ſleep;</hi> which Mr. <hi>VVoodward</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and ſuppoſing ſhe had called him, he aroſe, and came into the chamber where ſhe lay, and he declared that he ſaw the brightneſſes at his feet; and at that time the Voice ſaid, <hi>That the comprehenſive power of heaven,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A moſt blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous lie.</note> 
               <hi>was for that instant gathered into that room,</hi> and it alſo ſaid, <hi>All they that come before the preſence of the Lord, and are not pure, let them tremble.</hi> It was alſo revealed to her, that it would have been dangerous for Mr. <hi>VVoodward</hi> ſo to have come in at that time; had it not been for the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned meſſage that was to be done by him.</p>
            <p>In the morning ſhe ſpake to Mr. <hi>VVoodward</hi> to go to <hi>Rutlie</hi> and <hi>Bunnie,</hi> which he did, (for it ſeems all muſt be ready to ſerve her) but they made ſlight of the meſſage.</p>
            <p>But the woman <hi>VVaterman,</hi> ſhe ſaw in a viſion, and that ſhe had a great oven in her houſe, and ſhe had three looking glaſſes in the houſe, whereof one ſtood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the oven;
<note place="margin">A profound viſion and interpretation.</note> and it was interpreted to her, that theſe glaſſes were for Goody <hi>VVaterman</hi> to ſee her ſelfe in. This Goody <hi>VVaterman,</hi> though it doth not appear to me, that ſhe had any meſſenger ſent to her as the two men had; yet ſhe the next Sunday go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Andover, was with a great power drawne, even whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhe would or no to come to Crooxeaſon to <hi>M. Gadbury;</hi> whither when ſhe came, ſhe was in an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great ſweat,
<note place="margin">This is in the confeſſion, and doth not this look like a piece of Witchcraft?</note> but knew not the end of her coming; ſhe ſtayed there all night, and in the evening ſitting by the fire ſide, ſhe ſaid aloud, <hi>O Lord that I may not be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</hi> She fetcht her breath ſhort, ſhe cried out, Miſtreſſe <hi>VVoodward,</hi> Miſtreſſe <hi>Woodward,</hi> why keep you me here in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? at which words <hi>M. Gadbury</hi> ſaid; that ſhe her ſelfe wept exceedingly, and declared concerning this Goody <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terman,</hi> that ſhe was even<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> rent and torn in pieces; and ſhe cried out and ſaid, <hi>O Lord how canſt thou bring downe the ſtrongeſt heart that is?</hi> Rutlie <hi>is ſo high and ſtrong, yet the Lord can bring him downe, and that ſhe had fought againſt the Lord, and now could not but confeſſe that it was he.</hi> And thus
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:117821:15"/>Goody <hi>VVaterman,</hi> notwithſtanding her long ſtanding off,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Here end thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations I had from the large confeſſion of</hi> Mary Gadbury <hi>ſo often mentioned.</hi>
               </note> and great oppoſition ſhe ſometime made againſt them, is at length deluded, and brought over to them by their deceits.</p>
            <p>This effect of their deceits on this wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, is now the more advantagious to them, they having at leaſt ſeemingly been ſo much before oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by her. And what from the thing it ſelfe, and the ſtrange manner of it, it now works on Mr. <hi>VVoodward</hi> the Miniſter, in whoſe houſe theſe perſons were entertained, and who therefore was privy to all theſe proceedings; for (as I have heard himſelfe relate it in his own confeſſion before the Judge of Aſſize, where being charged to give credit to theſe deceits of <hi>Frankelin,</hi> and for declaring him to be the Chriſt) he acknowledged himſelfe for ſometime to be much troubled, not able to cloſe with what was by them delivered: that he asked of <hi>Frankelin</hi> whether he were the Chriſt; and that <hi>Frankelin</hi> ſhould an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>that that was not the body of Chriſt, but he had the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as a lion, Chriſt as a Lamb ſet at his breſt, and that he was now come to call in beleevers:</hi> he farther confeſſed, that after this, being much troubled he went to his barn, and there ſate down; where a perfect audible voice was heard by him, which ſaid unto him, <hi>ariſe, and declare what thou hast ſeen;</hi> yet that he kept his own counſell notwithſtanding, and declared this to no other, but that afterward Goody <hi>VVaterman</hi> comes and tells them that <hi>Frankelin</hi> was one borne at Overton, and was a Seducer, and in a railing manner went away from him; but that they [<hi>viz. Frankelin</hi> and <hi>Gadbury</hi>] ſaid that ſhe would be ſorry for it, and ſee her errour, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout foure or five dayes after Goody <hi>Waterman</hi> came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, deſiring to ſee God in all, and that the third time of her coming ſhe ſate downe on a ſtoole, and was there the whole afternoon, and at night going away ſhe ſaid ſhe could not, but was in priſon and bondage, and afterward declared to them that Satan was poſſeſſed of her, but that now ſhe was delivered; and (ſaid ſhe) the power that I reproached,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:117821:16"/>that hath delivered me, and this (ſaid M. <hi>Woodward</hi>) ſeized ſo on my ſpirit, that it cauſed me to entertain what I am now char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged withall. This of Mr. <hi>Woodwards</hi> confeſſion I heard declared by him to the Judge, and tooke it alſo in ſhort hand as well as I poſſibly could in ſuch a crowd of people: And by this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of his it appeares, that what by the glorious things he had ſeen, as he pretended, and by the things which the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons themſelves declared to him, as alſo that of the Voice which he heard, and theſe paſſages of this woman, they ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhe would be ſorry for what ſhe had done againſt them; and ſhe her ſelf afterward making ſuch a confeſſion concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, and ſo believing in them, all this cauſed Mr. <hi>Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> alſo to give up his Faith to them, as his wife had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore given him example of it: And queſtionleſſe, as in the beginning the woman was firſt in the tranſgreſſion, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deceived her ſelfe ſerved Satan as an inſtrument to deceive her husband alſo; ſo that this woman Mrs. <hi>VVoodward,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been firſt deluded, (as you have read) did contribute her utmoſt aſſiſtance to theſe deceivers to deale with, and to prevail upon her husband to deceive him alſo, and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly together they thus prevailed in it.</p>
            <p>Moſt of theſe paſſages thus before related, of the viſions of <hi>M. Gadbury,</hi> and concerning Goody <hi>VVaterman,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>VVoodward,</hi> happened in the time of <hi>VV. Franklins</hi> being at London, where he ſtayes not long, but as being herein very punctuall in his word and promiſe, at his appointed time downe he returnes again to viſit his Conſort, to ſee how their deſigne did thrive, as alſo to afford what aſſiſtance he could, to the further advancing and carrying of it on: In all the time of his abode at Crooxeaſon he is very diligent, not in diſcourſes only, but ſundry times preaching there in Mr. <hi>VVood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> houſe, thereby drawing together the more company unto him: And indeed by reaſon of the ſtrangeneſſe of the report carried about the Countrey concerning theſe perſons, and the things done by them, multitudes of perſons now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort to Mr. <hi>Woodwards,</hi> to ſee, heare, and ſpeake with them, of whom ſome come only for the novelty of the buſineſſe, and to ſatisfie themſelves with the ſight of ſuch ſtrange perſons; ſome as not crediting the things reported, to conferre with
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:117821:16"/>the perſons themſelves for their better aſſurance; but others being credulous perſons, wavering and uncertaine in matters of Religion, having itching ears after ſome new things, were ſoon drawne away and ſeduced by them: For now (beſides the perſons before mentioned Mr. <hi>Woodward</hi> and his wife Goody <hi>VVaterman</hi>) divers others do alſo become their Proſelites, as <hi>John Noyce, Edward Spradbury</hi> of Andover, <hi>Henry Dixon</hi> of Stockbridge, with ſeverall others; how theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons were wrought upon, and ſeduced by them, I have not certaine information, onely that I have heard in generall concerning them, eſpecially of <hi>Edward Spradbury,</hi> that ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſtrange ſights or viſions, and ſomthing of ſeeming-glorious appearance was ſeen by him in them, which is ſuppoſed to be that which chiefly prevailed upon him and others of them.</p>
            <p>But now doth this poyſonous infection begin amaine to ſpread it ſelfe, having gotten many, and theſe alſo very active perſons, to be the Preachers, ſpreaders, and publiſhers of it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad to the people: Theſe do even make it their buſineſſe to publiſh it to perſons whom they may have any occaſion to do withall, and to aſſert it with abundance of confidence, as what is firmly believed by them, and which with all the reaſon they can, they perſwade others to imbrace and entertain alſo, that he (that is this <hi>Franklin</hi>) is the Son of God, the Chriſt, the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> the Lamb ſlaine from the foundation, that ſuffered on the Croſſe, and was the Lion of the Tribe of Judah, and had the key of the bottomleſſe pit, that openeth and no man ſhutteth, and ſhutteth and no man openeth, &amp;c. with many other ſuch like blaſphemous expreſſions publiſhed by them concerning him. Theſe had alſo their ſeverall offices and titles accordingly given them; ſo that <hi>John Noyce</hi> was <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, ſent forth to tell that <hi>Chriſt was come upon the earth; Henry Dix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> office was to be one of the deſtroying Angells mentioned in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> ſent forth to curſe the earth, and the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of it, and his uſuall curſes were in a moſt execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble manner, to bid the Plague of God be upon the heart of perſons, and the Devill to take them: Thus Mr. <hi>George Potti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary,</hi> an honeſt godly man in this Countrey informed me, that he ſo curſed me in a conference with him. In an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:117821:17"/>I have in writing ſent to me from <hi>Thomas Wilkins,</hi> Conſtable of Andover, he writes to me thus:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dixon</hi> ſaid, that there was neither God nor Devill, and that all things came by nature, and did curſe me with theſe curſes, the Plague of God upon thy heart, the Devill take thee; he ſaid that I ſhould be damned in three weeks, and that I ſhould come howling and crying, and wiſh that I could touch the lower hemme of his garment; and he ſaid of himſelfe, that he was the deſtroying Angell ſent to curſe the earth: Thus the Information of <hi>Thomas Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now <hi>Edward Spradbury</hi> had gotten a ſomewhat better office; for <hi>William Franklin</hi> ſaid, that he was one of the two Witneſſes mentioned in the 11. of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> as <hi>John Lewis</hi> hath in writing to me certified, adding that he would teſtifie it upon Oath, but the uſuall office of this <hi>Spradbury</hi> was to bee an healing Angell; and ſo what <hi>Dix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> had in the diſcharge of his office curſed and deſtroyed, he came as an healing Angell to heale and reſtore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; wherefore when any perſon did diſcover offence at theſe curſes, and horrid imprecations by <hi>Dixon</hi> uttered, he would tell them they ſhould not be offended at it, that it was his office, and what he did therein was but the diſcharge of his office, but that he himſelfe was the healing Angell: Of this wicked ſociety was alſo one <hi>William Holmes</hi> of Houghton, he ſeems to be a part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>Dixons</hi> in his office of being a deſtroying An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell.</p>
            <p>Here take a true account of what paſſed between him, and one Mr. <hi>Burret</hi> a Miniſter, being in the Pariſh of Houghton, which I have aſſerted under Mr. <hi>Burrets</hi> owne hand thus:</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:117821:17"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="account">
                        <head>Houghton, Jan. <hi>17. 1649.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>The day and year above written coming to two men which I had at work, there was talking with them <hi>William Holmes,</hi> junior, of <hi>Houghton,</hi> having a gun in his hand, and in his mouth many hard ſpeeches and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies againſt God; amongſt the which, at my firſt approach, this was the firſt, That he was one of the Vials of Gods wrath, to confound Mr <hi>Warren,</hi> my ſelf, and the reſt of the Pariſh, which he ſaid were all damned: Upon my reply, <hi>I pray you William leave theſe fond and ſtrong deluſions, and have God in your heart:</hi> He anſwered, <hi>What doſt thou know what God is?</hi> (or to that purpoſe:) <hi>God is a Toad, a Snake,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">O horrid blaſphemy!</note> 
                           <hi>and a Devil.</hi> At which words I left the place, and upon it, which can witneſs the ſame, and more,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>John Butler,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Daniel Crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>and <hi>Robert Holmes.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Ita teſtatur, Chriſtophorus Burret.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>I was alſo credibly informed, that at the ſame time when he uttered theſe fearful Blaſphemies, he alſo added thereto this grievous curſe, <hi>The plague of God confound thee and thy Religion.</hi> Oh what an height of impiety and boldneſs in wickedneſs are theſe perſons thus come unto! whoſe heart can but tremble at ſuch grievous Blaſphemies againſt the Divine Majeſty, and wonder at the wonderful patience and long-ſuffering of God, ſo forbearing ſuch perſons, by whom his holy and glorious Name and Being is ſo grievouſly blaſphemed?</p>
            <p>This <hi>William Holmes</hi> having been formerly a very looſe and prophane young man, was ſo far wrought upon by the Miniſtry of Mr <hi>Warren,</hi> (who is Miniſter of that Pariſh) that he left his vicious courſes, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came very hopeful for Religion; but is now fallen into this depth of wickedneſs, enough to be ſo a warning to others, <hi>that he who thinketh he ſtandeth, take heed least he fall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus the leaven and poyſon of this infection, diſperſed abroad by ſuch active publiſhers of it, begins to ſpread exceedingly, that too many now begin to be taken with it, that ſuch notice and great offence is juſtly taken thereat by divers godly and well affected Miniſters, and others, that they think it neceſſary for the peace of the County, now ready to be hereby endangered; as alſo for the good of Souls, and out of a tender affection to them; eſpecially for the Glory of God and Chriſt, whoſe Name and Honour is ſo ſtriken at, and grievouſly blaſpherned, to think upon ſome courſe, whereby to ſtop the further ſpreading of this ſo great an evil.</p>
            <p>Accordingly, the laſt Quarter Seſſions of the Peace holden in this City of <hi>Winton</hi> for this County of <hi>Southampton,</hi> in the beginning of <hi>January,</hi> many and great Informations and Complaints from ſundry well-affected
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:117821:18"/>peeple were there brought and preſented to the Gentlemen, Juſtices of the Peace for this County, then and there met together, concerning theſe practiſes of theſe perſons, deſiring juſtice againſt them, and ſome courſe thereby to be taken for the reſtraining of them. The Juſtices of the Peace (as in duty they ought) declared themſelves very ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of theſe things, and of the Glory of God, and good of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, ſo highly concerned in them: And accordingly with all ſpeed were Warrants granted out by ſeveral of them, to the Conſtables of thoſe parts, for the apprehending of <hi>William Franklin,</hi> and ſome others of theſe ſo dangerous perſons. Theſe Warrants were with as much ſpeed as might be put in execution by the Conſtables; by them were <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Franklin,</hi> and with him Mr <hi>Woodward, Henry Dixon, Edward Spradbury,</hi> apprehended: and beſides what was done towards theſe perſons upon their apprehenſion by the Bayliff of <hi>Andover,</hi> (where they were either apprehended firſt, or brought thither,) whoſe care and faithfulneſs in this buſineſs is much to be commended; they were from thence brought hither to <hi>Wincheſter</hi> upon Munday, <hi>Ianuary</hi> 27. and there preſented before thoſe Juſtices of the County, who live at this City, by them to be examined, and proceeded withal accordingly. With thoſe perſons thus apprehended, &amp; brought by the Warrant, came alſo others of their own accord, though not included in that Warrant, as <hi>M. Gadbury,</hi> Mrs <hi>Woodward,</hi> Goody <hi>Waterman</hi> and ſome others. I do not hear that <hi>Iohn Noyce</hi> was here preſent: particular complaint was made afterward againſt <hi>William Holmes,</hi> and particular Warrant grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the apprehending of him, but he either departing from his habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, or ſome way or other hiding himſelf, was not at all yet appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, that he neither appeared now, or at any time, before the Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or at the Aſſize. But thoſe perſons who were thus apprehended, with the others that came ſo together with them, not ſo much to ſee what would be done with them, as to aſſiſt them, and witneſs the ſame thing with them in their Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al and Examinations, and together they came with abundance of confidence and boldneſs, to ſtick unto thoſe things which they had aſſerted &amp; with which they knew they ſhould be accuſed. The Juſtices before whom they were brought, and by whom they were now to be examined, were Mr <hi>Thomas Betteſworth,</hi> and Mr <hi>Richard Gobbe;</hi> Their Appearance and Examination was at Mr <hi>Bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toſworths</hi> houſe, who lives in the Cloſe here at <hi>Wincheſter:</hi> At the time of their Examination great multitudes of perſons reſorted to the houſe, to ſee and hear what would be done with them, or ſaid by them.</p>
            <p>It would be tedious to the Reader, and that which the brevity I
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:117821:18"/>deſire, and ſhall endeavour in this Relation, will not bear, ſhould I now proceed largely to ſet down the whole of their carriage before the Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and of the things ſpoken by them, according to that credible informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I received of it: But ſome moſt material paſſages I ſhall have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect unto, together with the Examinations of ſome Witneſſes taken upon Oath, and the Examinations of the perſons themſelves atteſted by them, by ſubſcribing their names to them: Theſe will be the moſt authentique Teſtimonies I can preſent my Reader withall of the blaſphemous ſpeeches and practiſes of theſe perſons; and wherein he may ſee, from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions of the perſons themſelves, a Confirmation of the moſt or moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial things that have been before related.</p>
            <p>As concerning their carriage before the Juſtices, it was with abundance of boldneſs and confidence; in general there aſſerting whatſoever had been before declared by them, and towards others whom they had occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to converſe withall, with abundance of ſcorn and contempt: Goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Waterman,</hi> a very talkative woman, ſaid to the company, That if they were not there, the houſe would fall down upon them, and if they ſhould not ſpeak, the ſtones would ſpeak: And being very forward in ſpeaking after this manner, Mrs <hi>Woodward</hi> told her, That ſhe ſaw much of the Power of God, in carrying her forth to ſpeak ſo as ſhe did. This Goody <hi>Waterman,</hi> to one that bid her ſtand farther from him, ſaying, that her breath did ſtink, anſwered, that ſhe defied what he ſpake, and her breath was the breath of the Lord: And concerning another young wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, one of their own company, who had ſpoken ſomewhat wherein ſhe was contradicted, ſhe alſo anſwered, That what that young woman ſpake was not much to be regard, ſhe being but a babe of a week old; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it was their manner to reckon their age from the time of their firſt believing in this Deceiver, as if they had been but then born. When one ſpeaking of <hi>William Franklin,</hi> called him <hi>Fellow; Mary Gadbury</hi> at the hearing thereof, holding up her hand at him, ſaid, <hi>Thou dog, how dareſt thou call thy Saviour Fellow; thou art not worthy of a crumb.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus may theſe, and many other ſuch like paſſages which fell from them, ſerve to diſcover their height of confidence in their blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous Aſſertions, as alſo the impudent boldneſs of their car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.</p>
            <p>But leaving theſe things, we will now proceed to the Confeſſions and Examinations of theſe perſons themſelves, and Witneſſes concerning them, ſetting down firſt what was atteſted by ſome Witneſſes, and next what were their own Confeſſions.</p>
            <p>And firſt take here the Teſtimony of <hi>Fortunatus Wats</hi> of <hi>Woodhay,</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:117821:19"/>who was the firſt that I can hear of to have given evidence againſt theſe perſons, and his evidence had been given in to the Juſtices before they granted their Warrants for the apprehending of theſe perſons; but may now be here very fitly inſerted. His Evidence was thus.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="evidence">
                        <p>A man aged about thirty or fourty years, on <hi>Monday</hi> the 17. of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi> 1649. at Mr <hi>Woodwards</hi> at <hi>Crooxeaſon</hi> in <hi>Hampſhire,</hi> affirmed himſelf to be <hi>Chriſt, the Son of the living God; the Meſſiah that ſits at the right Hand of God; the Corner ſtone, the Lamb of God, that was ſlain at Ieruſalem, and had the wound yet on his body unhealed:</hi> That his <hi>Spirit was abroad, gathering in of Souls;</hi> that he <hi>came now in the fulneſs of time to ſave the very Elect, and is none of thoſe falſe</hi> Chriſts <hi>ſpoken of in Scripture, but the true</hi> Chriſt <hi>indeed:</hi> If any would know my name, <hi>I am,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>the great King of Heaven, without any guile in my mouth, without beginning of time, or end of days.</hi> He under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took to forgive ſins;</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>and by name did ſo to me <hi>Fortunatus Wats</hi> of <hi>Woodhay</hi> in <hi>Hampſhire,</hi> Witneſs my hand, <date>
                                 <hi>Decemb.</hi> 20. 1649.</date> And this he ſubſcribed his name unto,</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Now you ſhall have the Examination of ſome Witneſſes, delivered upon Oath before the Juſtices, at <hi>Andover</hi> and at <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> after their Apprehenſion.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="accusation">
                        <head>The accuſation of <hi>Peter Blake</hi> of <hi>Andover</hi> in the County of <hi>Southampton,</hi> Merchant, given upon Oath before ſeveral Juſtices of the Peace at <hi>Andover,</hi> the <hi>26.</hi> of <hi>January, 1649.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>HE ſaith upon Oath, That <hi>Edward Spradbury</hi> of <hi>Andover,</hi> Cloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worker, affirmed, that one lately lying at the <hi>Star</hi> in <hi>Andover</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, naming himſelf <hi>Franklin,</hi> was, <hi>the Lord of Life and Glory: and that he was the Meſſiah, the Lamb ſlain from the foundation; that he had the key of the bottomleſs pit, that ſhutteth and no man openeth, and openeth and no man ſhutteth: That he was the Chriſt, the Saviour of the World; The Chriſt that ſuffered on the Croſs: The Lion of the Tribe of Judah.</hi> And this, and more to the like purpoſe, was ſpoken by the ſaid <hi>Edward Spradbury,</hi> in the hearing of the ſaid <hi>Peter Blake,</hi> at the dwelling houſe of the ſaid <hi>Edward Spradbury</hi> in <hi>Andover</hi> aforeſaid, on Monday the 21. of <hi>January,</hi> 1649.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Peter Blake.</hi> For ſo he ſubſcribed his name.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:117821:19"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="examination">
                        <head>The Examination of <hi>Richard Cook</hi> against <hi>Henry Dixon,</hi> January <hi>26.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>He ſaith upon Oath, that <hi>Henry Dixon</hi> ſaid this preſent Evening in <hi>Andover,</hi> in this Accuſants preſence, and divers others, <hi>That he the ſaid</hi> Dixon <hi>was the God of Light, and the God himſelf.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>And now alſo did <hi>Thomas Wilkins</hi> deliver in that teſtimony of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, wherein he ſo affirmed upon Oath, this <hi>Dixon</hi> to ſay, <hi>That there was neither God nor Devil, but all things came by nature:</hi> Such a Spirit of frenzy and contradiction, as well as Blaſphemy, poſſeſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth theſe perſons, as in the ſame breath, to affirm, <hi>That there is no God; and yet that he himſelf is God: That there is neither God nor Devil;</hi> and yet preſently in his curſing to uſe the names of both of them.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="examination">
                        <head>The Examination of <hi>John Lewis</hi> taken before the Justices.</head>
                        <p>He ſaith, that <hi>William Woodward</hi> of <hi>Crooxeaſon,</hi> Miniſter, ſaid, that the man who was at his houſe, being one named <hi>Franklin,</hi> was <hi>the Lord of Life and Glory:</hi> and that he had received glorious things from him: and that one who beleeved him not to be ſo, was afterward convinced, and came to ſee the glory of the Lord, and acknowledged him to be the Lord of glory. He farther ſaith, That <hi>Edward Spradbury</hi> told him, that <hi>Franklin</hi> ſaid in his preſence, <hi>that he had troden the winepreſs of the wrath of God; and that he the ſaid</hi> Edward Spradbury <hi>was one of the two Witneſſes mentioned in the Revelation; that he was ſlain for the testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> and that the ſaid man, named <hi>Franklin,</hi> was <hi>ſlain, dead, and riſen again in glory.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>I have moreover an information which this <hi>John Lewis</hi> ſent me under his hand, concerning the ſame thing, declaring that <hi>William Franklin</hi> ſhould ſay, <hi>That he was the Lord of Life and Glory; that he was the Lamb ſlain from the foundation; that he was the ever-living Son of the Father; that he had the key of the bottomleſs pit: that it was he who dyed without the gates of Jeruſalem.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>This I <hi>John Lewis</hi> certifie upon my Oath.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:117821:20"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="examination">
                        <head>The Examination and Evidence of Mr <hi>Thomas Muſprat</hi> of Wincheſter.</head>
                        <p>He affirmeth, that being at <hi>Andover,</hi> he found Mr <hi>William Woodward</hi> with one <hi>Spradbury,</hi> and one <hi>Dixon,</hi> who joyntly affirmed, that the ſaid <hi>Franklin</hi> was <hi>the Christ, and Saviour of mankinde:</hi> And he the ſaid <hi>Thomas Musprat</hi> finding fault with Mr <hi>Woodward</hi> to be in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny with ſuch men, he the ſaid Mr <hi>Woodward</hi> replyed, <hi>That he had ſeen the glory of the ſaid</hi> Franklin, <hi>and did rejoyce in it:</hi> Whereupon the ſaid <hi>Thomas</hi> anſwered, <hi>that all glory was created or uncreated,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded which of theſe two he had ſeen in the ſaid <hi>Franklin;</hi> to which, after ſome waving the queſtion, he at laſt anſwered, <hi>that it was the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>created glory.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>This Evidence of Mr <hi>Musprats</hi> was given by him upon Oath, before the Judg of Aſſize alſo, and then I heard his Evidence, and taking it in writing, finde it ſomewhat more full then this which I have thus tranſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed from the Juſtices Record of it, at leaſt in the firſt part of it: for up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Oath then he declared, that being ſo in <hi>Andover,</hi> theſe perſons <hi>(viz.)</hi> Mr <hi>Woodward, Dixon, Spradbury,</hi> joyntly affirmed to him, <hi>Franklin to be the Son of God:</hi> upon which he diſtinguiſhed of Sons of God by Adoption and by Nature; and would know of them, in which of theſe reſpects they would have that man to be the Son of God: They thus anſwered to him, that they knew nothing of that diſtinction; but that <hi>Franklin,</hi> whom you ſo call, is <hi>the Son of God, and Saviour of the World.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Thus I have related the Teſtimonies and Evidences of ſeveral of the Witneſſes, all which ſpeak very home, to diſcover the great Blaſphemy whereof theſe perſons are guilty. I ſhall now alſo ſet down their own Confeſſions in their Examinations before Mr <hi>Botteſworth</hi> and Mr <hi>Cobbe,</hi> the Juſtices, wherein you will ſee what theſe Witneſſes teſtified to be by themſelves aſſerted, that in a caſe ſo clear, as their own Confeſſion makes it, we ſhall not need further witneſſes, now hearing themſelves ſpeak.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="examination">
                        <head>The Examination of <hi>Edward Spradbury</hi> of Andover, Clothworker.</head>
                        <p>He affirmed, that the man, whom ſome men call <hi>Franklin,</hi> is <hi>the Meſſiah, the Lamb ſlain from the Foundation; and that he had the key of the bottomleſs pit, that he ſhutteth and no man openeth, and openeth and no man ſhutteth; the Lion of the Tribe of Iudah.</hi> He affirmed that
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:117821:20"/>he heard the man, whom ſome men call <hi>Franklin,</hi> preach twice at the <hi>Star</hi> in <hi>Andover,</hi> and once at <hi>Croox-eaſon</hi> at Mr <hi>Woodwards,</hi> at all which ſeveral times he took Texts; but many other times he hath heard Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions from him without taking Texts.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="examination">
                        <head>The Examination of <hi>Henry Dixon</hi> of Stockbridg.</head>
                        <p>He affirmeth, that about a fortnight ſince, and not at any time before, he came acquainted with one which ſome men call <hi>Franklin,</hi> but he affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him to be <hi>the Son of God, the Chriſt crucified for our ſins, now come down from Heaven.</hi> He affirmeth, <hi>that he himſelf is one of the ſeven Angels ſpoken of in the Revelation; and that he is ſent to plague the Earth, and that he is ſent by God.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="examination">
                        <head>The Examination of Mr <hi>Woodward.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>He affirmeth, that <hi>Franklin,</hi> and the woman called <hi>Mary Gadbury,</hi> who came with him, did call themſelves man and wife, and that they lay together in one bed in his houſe about a fortnight.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="examination">
                        <head>The Examination of <hi>Margaret Woodward,</hi> wife to Mr <hi>William Woodward.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>She affirmeth, that the man examined before us, whom we called <hi>Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> is <hi>her Lord, and her King, and that ſhe is ſaved by his Death and Paſſion.</hi> Farther ſhe ſaith, <hi>That the man, her Saviour, was nothing but dry bones; his fleſh was clean ſcrap't away, and his skin and bone hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together: and his skin likewiſe very ſuddenly fell off from him, and that he had nothing left but the hair of his head, and of that one hair was not diminiſhed; and afterwards new fleſh came again as a young childe.</hi> She doth farther affirm, <hi>that there was a woman with him, which he call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his Spouſe, and others call her the Queen, and that they continued together, and lay together at her Houſe about a fortnight; and that ſhe was one night one hour in ſtrong travel, and brought forth a ſpiritual birth,</hi> which this Examinant received from her. She farther ſaith, That he did preach in her houſe two or three times, and that her family did hear him, and divers others; and that he did often deliver much ſpiritual diſcourſe, when he did not preach.</p>
                        <p>But not being ſatisfied with that Anſwer, in regard that it was ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected that ſhe was delivered of a childe, and had deſtroyed it, the Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were very earneſt with her to know the truth farther, and told her, they did beleeve there was ſubſtance in that birth, and that it was not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:117821:21"/>ſpiritual, and did expect that ſhe ſhould ſatisfie them in it, and tell them the Truth. She anſwered, that ſhe could beſt tell, in regard ſhe was preſent, and received what the Queen was delivered of; and ſaid, it was of that man which ſhe called <hi>Franklin,</hi> but in a ſpiritual manner, perſwading them that <hi>Franklin</hi> was transfigured, and had no ſubſtance left him; and that ſhe received him as a Saviour (from the woman called the Spouſe) in the ſhape of a man; and moreover told the Juſtices, that what was in the Scripture, of either Old or New Teſtament, was but Types and Shadows, which ſhe did not now regard, having the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Thus far the Examination and Confeſſion of Mrs <hi>Woodward,</hi> of whom it is to be noted, that when ſhe was called in by the Juſtices to be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by them, <hi>Mary Gadbury</hi> calling her, ſaid, <hi>Come in my Elect Lady:</hi> And Goody <hi>Waterman,</hi> the woman ſo often before mentioned, ſaid then of her ſelf alſo, that ſhe was <hi>the Kings Daughter, all glorious within.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let us now come to thoſe who were the Principals in all this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and conſider what was done with them.</p>
            <p>Concerning them therfore it is to be known, that the Juſtices had much to do with them to get an Anſwer from them to any the queſtions they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, concerning their Names, Conditions, Callings, Habitations: they would either anſwer, they had no name, no habitation, according to the fleſh, intimating thereby that they were wholly ſpiritual, the fleſh wholly deſtroyed in them; and thereby all theſe things of name, relation, habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which were fleſhly alſo. But it being intimated to them by one of the Juſtices, that they muſt then deal with them as with Rogues, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting them to <hi>Bridewel,</hi> the houſe of Correction; for ſo it ſeems the Law doth judg thoſe to be Rogues, that being examined, cannot, or will not, declare their names, conditions, calling, or place of their habitations, and accordingly appoints the Houſe of Correction for them. <hi>William Franklin</hi> therefore being ſoon ſenſible of this, and the danger he was in thereby, receded from his before profeſſed Reſolution, and now became willing to ſubmit to Examination, and accordingly being examined, made this following Confeſſion.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="deposition">
                        <head>The Examination of <hi>William Franklin,</hi> taken the <hi>28.</hi> of January, <hi>1649.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>He ſaith, his Living is at <hi>Stepney,</hi> beyond <hi>London,</hi> and that he is by Trade a Rope-maker; and that he hath now, according to the fleſh, a wife and three children living. He ſaith farther, that about a moneth ſince
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:117821:21"/>he went to the houſe of Mr <hi>William Woodward,</hi> a Miniſter, at <hi>Croex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſon,</hi> and that he had a woman with him, which he calleth his Spouſe, and hath been acquainted with her a long time: And doth affirm, That it was revealed to him in a Viſion, that ſhe ſhould be ſet apart for his uſe, and that he ſhould ſeparate from his own wife; which ſhe the ſaid Spouſe at the firſt motion, having a great opinion of his integrity, believed, and conſented to go with him whither he pleaſed. And immediately after they had another Viſion, whereby they were warned to go into the Hill Country, into the Land of <hi>Ham,</hi> which they interpreted to be into <hi>Hamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire;</hi> and ſo being obedient unto that heavenly Viſion, they came both together in <hi>Hunts</hi> Wagon to <hi>Andover.</hi> He farther ſaith, That he often preached at Mr <hi>Woodwards</hi> houſe in the preſence of Mr <hi>Woodward,</hi> and his wife, and whole family, and ſometimes twenty more, and ſometimes more: And ſaith, That he is the Son of God, and was crucified without the gates at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and that his body hath been wounded, broken, and often offered up for ſin, and that it was about three years and an half ſince that he aſſumed this fleſhly body of his, and that he is not to ſuffer any more in this mortal body. It being told him That he could not be the Chriſt, Chriſt being in Heaven at the right hand of the Father, as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture teſtifieth, but he being here bodily muſt be a Deceiver, he anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Thoſe things of the Scripture were gone, and were nothing to him but types and ſhadows.</hi> And thus you have alſo the Examination and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of <hi>W. Franklin.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>But <hi>Mary Gadbury,</hi> not ſo ſenſible of the danger ſhe ſhould expoſe her ſelf unto, by refuſing to be examined, and concealing her name and habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion when required of her, refuſed ſtill to give any direct Anſwer to thoſe things: and therefore all that I can underſtand at this time to be anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by her, was, to that of her name, that ſhe had no name according to the fleſh, but a new name; to that concerning her husband, (there being ground enough to judg that ſhe had an husband,) that ſhe had now no husband according to the fleſh, but that her maker was her husband, the Lord of Hoſts was his name, and he was within her: and being queſtioned concerning her lying with <hi>Franklin</hi> every night, though he were a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried man, as it had been witneſſed their ſo lying together, which though ſhe could not deny, yet ſhe affirmed, that it was without pollution or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filement, and denyed that there had been any carnal copulation between them. Speaking of <hi>William Franklin,</hi> ſhe affirmed, that he was crucified at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and being demanded whether ſhe had been at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and when, ſhe anſwered, that ſhe had been there about a week ago; of which her Anſwer ſhe afterward gave this Reaſon, ſaying, that <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was every where. And this is the whole that I can find to have been
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:117821:22"/>then taken of her Examination.</p>
                        <p>But that one thing of the womans impudence is moreover noted, which is, That it being ſuppoſed by many who were preſent at her Examination, that ſhe was painted, her complexion being ſo very freſh and beautiful: that the truth thereof might be diſcovered, one of the Juſtices took a candle, (for this their Examination was at night,) and told her, that ſhe looked ſo fair, that he did ſcarce believe it to be natural; whereupon ſhe ſtept forth preſently, and very boldly put her face very near to the candle, and ſaid, That ſhe was glad the glory of God did ſhine ſo beight in her face, that they were forced to admire it.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>The Examination of theſe ſeveral perſons being now thus paſt, the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices deſigned and endeavored, if poſſible, to obtain from <hi>William Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> the head of this blaſphemous company, ſome Recantation of theſe his many Blaſphemies, and ſome acknowledgment of his great evil therein, hoping that ſuch an Acknowledgment and Recantation from him, the Ring-leader, might be a means to ſtartle all the reſt of the ſeduced party, that ſo followed him, and hung upon him; to this purpoſe they begin to deal with him: They ſet before him the danger he had now brought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into by theſe his wicked practiſes, and endeavor to make him ſenſible, that there is no way for him to obtain favour, to ſave himſelf from the great danger he was in, and to recover liberty, unleſs he be ſenſible, and make acknowledgment of his wickedneſs, in theſe abominable practiſes, to the undeceiving of others; and put him alſo in hope, that by this means ſome favour might be obtained by him. And indeed <hi>William Franklin,</hi> now at length becoming ſenſible of his condition, and the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and danger which he nad plunged himſelf into, apprehends it his beſt way to hearken to the advice of the Juſtices, as the only means left him to ſave himſelf, and to obtain favour: And therefore doth he, in anſwer to that adviſe of theirs, pretend himſelf to be ſenſible of the evil of the way he had thus walked in, and profeſſeth himſelf (at leaſt outwardly and ſeemingly) willing to make ſuch an Acknowledgment and Recantation as they propoſed to him, hoping and expecting thereby (as it appears) to find favour from them. This therefore of his profeſſion being accepted of, a form of a Recantation is preſently by Juſtice <hi>Betteſworth</hi> drawn up, offered to him, and is, in the very words of it, ſubſcribed unto by him.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="recantation">
                        <head>The Recantation of <hi>William Franklin.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>He now confeſſeth, that he is ſorry that he hath affirmed himſelf to be Chriſt, and that he was crucified for the ſins of all men, and that there was no ſalvation but by faith in him, and doth heartily repent, and doth himſelf hope to be ſaved by the merits of Jeſus Christ crucified, as in the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:117821:22"/>Gospel is ſet forth unto us, and that he will openly recant from his former blaſphemous Opinions; and cauſe all that have been miſled by him, to the uttermoſt of his power, to forſake the falſe Opinions and Deluſions which he hath brought them into.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>To this he ſubſcribed his name, <hi>William Franklin;</hi> adding alſo thereunto theſe, or words to the like purpoſe, That what he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed now in this his Recantation, he intended by the Grace of God to ſtand unto.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>By this Recantation preſently a great diſtraction aroſe amongſt the whole party; nor can it be imagined, but that they ſhould be much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded hereat, not knowing themſelves what to do, aſhamed ſo ſuddenly to renounce what but even now with ſo much con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>dence they aſſerted, and yet how to ſtick to it they knew not, he that was the head of their party having ſo ſoon and ſolemnly (as it appeared) diſclaimed what either he of himſelf, or they concerning him had thus aſſerted, reckoning them to be but blaſphemous Opinions; no wonder therefore that they are ſo confounded, and know not what to do. <hi>Mary Gadbury,</hi> when this was firſt ſhewn to her by the Juſtices, at the very time of it, looking upon <hi>Franklin</hi> with a very angry countenance, demanded, <hi>Haſt thou done this? is this thy hand?</hi> At which he remaining ſome time ſilent, at laſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>You ſee what the times are; Or, you ſee what condition we are fallen into.</hi> She alſo afterward often times profeſſed, That ſhe ſhould never have believed this, though ten thouſand had told her ſo, had ſhe not her ſelf ſeen it; That ſhe ſhould have layd down her life for the truth of what ſhe had declared concerning him, who did now ſee her ſelf to be abuſed by him; ſhe kept not company with him as <hi>Franklin,</hi> but was perſwaded by him, that that name and nature was gone, that he would not be called by that name, and now to ſee him ſubſcribe the name of <hi>William Franklin,</hi> and that alſo to ſuch a Recantation, made her ſee, that ſhe had been deceived by him. <hi>Edward Spradbury,</hi> when he came to the ſight of it, looking as angerly upon <hi>Franklin,</hi> yea holding up his hand at him, as if he would have ſtriken him, ſaid, <hi>Thou Villain, how haſt thou deceived us by thy lyes?</hi> And thus he that even now was their Lord and Chriſt, their Saviour, that dyed for their ſins, is preſently, even in the ſame inſtant of time and place, reckoned a Villain, that by lyes deceived them: So uncertain, ſo changeable, are theſe giddy people, and upon ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>andy foundations is their whole ſalvation layd by them. And Mr <hi>Woodward,</hi> who before pretended that he ſaw his uncreated glory, and rejoyced at it, could now preſently upon this ſay, That he thought there was Witchcraft in it, and ſuppoſed they were Witches<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Such a ſudden change, ſuch a great confuſion is thus on a ſudden wrought among them.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:117821:23"/>
            <p>After theſe things of the Examinations of theſe Perſons and Witneſſes was thus over, the Juſtices proceeded to diſpoſe of the perſons themſelves, and it was thus: That Mr <hi>Woodward, Edward Spradbury, Henry Dixon,</hi> were bound over to the Aſſize, then to appear, and before the Judg to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer theſe and ſuch like things they ſhould be charged withall: but <hi>William Franklin</hi> and <hi>Mary Gadbury</hi> were both of them committed to priſon, upon ſuſpition of having the one two wives, the other two huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands; which ſuſpition and commitment of theirs thereupon was upon very good grounds, and very juſt; for <hi>Franklin</hi> acknowledged in his Confeſſion his having a wife and three children, and there was ſufficient information of the woman, that ſhe had an husband alſo; and yet for theſe thus to accompany together, to call one another husband and wife, and as husband and wife ordinarily to lie together, could not but be juſt ground for ſuch a ſuſpicion and commitment upon it: <hi>William Franklin</hi> therefore, having his <hi>Mittimus</hi> made, is preſently ſent to the Common-Goal, where he is received, and as a Felon, (being thus committed upon juſt ſuſpicion of Felony,) hath irons upon his legs, and in this condition continues ſo fettered in priſon till the time of the Aſſize: but <hi>Mary Gad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> having ſo accompanied with another womans husband, and beſides the Charge of that ſuſpected Felony and Adultery, refuſing to declare her name or condition, is as a lewd woman, &amp; rogue in law, committed firſt to Bridewell, the houſe of Correction, where ſhe lay a week, and in that ſpace ſeveral times received the Correction of the houſe, according to the cuſtom of it: The Munday after, <hi>February</hi> 4. ſhe is ſent for thence by the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices, and brought before them: And having now ſuffered a little hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and taſted ſome what of the ſmart of the whip, the height of her ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit begins to be ſomewhat abated; now ſhe with abundance of tears la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments her condition wherein ſhe is, and deſires all favour that may be from the Juſtices; ſhe doth now readily anſwer to all their Interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories concerning her name, her calling, her husband and children, her ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with this man, and the occaſion of their coming into this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; all which was ſuch as I have before related concerning her, that therefore it may be ſomewhat tedious here again to relate and inſert it: And beſides what ſhe ſpoke to the Juſtices in anſwer to theſe and the like queſtions, as that which might ſerve them in their proceedings in Law with her: She was very forward of her own accord to declare ſuch things which they (becauſe they concerned not them in their proceedings) liſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not much after: but therein diſcourſing ſo at large, as ſhe did of her Viſions, Revelations, Voyces; I, who was there by, had the patience to hear her at leaſt two hours diſcourſing and relating of ſuch things, and what ſhe ſpake, I writ from her own mouth, being willing thereby to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:117821:23"/>learn ſomewhat of the wiles of <hi>Satan,</hi> whereby ſhe and others by her had been deceived: and thus I received from her ſelf at this time that large Confeſsion ſo often before mentioned, whence I have preſented ſo many things already to the Reader.</p>
            <p>After all this of her Confeſsion, is ſhe dealt withall as <hi>Franklin</hi> had been, to procure ſome acknowledgment and <hi>Recantation</hi> from her; and beſides the Arguments wherewith he had been perſwaded, now uſed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards her alſo, it is farther preſſed by the example of what <hi>Franklin</hi> had done; and ſhe pretending to be willing thereunto, a form of a <hi>Recanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> was preſently drawn up, preſented or read to her, acknowledged and ſubſcribed by her: And it was thus:</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="recantation">
                        <head>The Recantation of <hi>Mary Gadbury.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I</hi> Mary Gadbury <hi>do hereby acknowledg, that I have been deceived by the temptations of the evil one, the Devil, in a ſinful way accompanying with one</hi> William Franklin, <hi>a married man, and aſcribing to him what is proper to CHRIST; And do declare my ſelf heartily ſorry, that I ever ſpoke of him under the names of my Lord, and my Christ, which I have ſinfully given unto him: And renouncing theſe and all ſuch deceits, I profeſs my ſelf to beleeve in</hi> the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Son of God, and Saviour of his people, <hi>who is now in Heaven at the right Hand of the Father, by whoſe Righteouſneſs alone I hope and expect to obtain Life, and everlaſting Salvation.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>To this her <hi>Recantation</hi> ſhe ſubſcribed by making her mark, ſhe having not skill to write her name.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>And now upon this, is this woman removed from <hi>Bridewel</hi> to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Gaol, whither <hi>Franklin</hi> had been before committed, upon ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Felony, as hath been before related; and ſo theſe two companions in wickedneſs, after the ſeveral places they had been in, though a week ſeparated, are now met together in the Gaol, where they lie expecting the Aſſize, then to be either releaſed, or otherwiſe according to Law dealt withall.</p>
            <p>While theſe perſons thus lay in priſon together, between the time of their Commitment and the Aſſize, about the ſpace of five weeks, they were by great multitudes of perſons from divers places, reſorted unto and viſited, but for ſeveral ends; Some to ſatisfie themſelves in the ſight of thoſe who had ſo filled the Country with the rumour and report of the ſtrangeneſs of their Actions and Opinions: Others, that were godly, and ſetled in Religion, to confer with them, to enquire into the Principles
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:117821:24"/>whereby they were acted, to finde out the wiles of <hi>Satan,</hi> whereby they and others by them had been deceived; and if poſſible to convince them the more of the greatneſs of that evil whereof they were thus guilty. Some again, out of reſpect to them, did often viſit them; for they want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not thoſe (no not in this City) who (as foul as their Crimes were) would ſpeak and plead for them; did look upon them as perſons wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and perſecuted: and by theſe was proviſion ſent in dayly unto them, whereby they were (the woman at leaſt) as well ſupplied with neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, as if at liberty. Notwithſtanding theſe ſufferings, which theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons had thus fallen into, and diſcovery made thereby of their ſo ſinful and abominable practiſes and blaſphemies, yet was all the endevor that might be uſed to keep up the hearts of their parties abroad: For the more credit of which I ſhall here inſert a Paſſage of a Letter, written by one, ſometime a Cavalier in Arms in <hi>Wallingford</hi> Gariſon againſt the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> but ſince his diſcharge of that ſervice married a wife, pretended ſomewhat to Religion, in a ſhort time run through divers Sects and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, forſook his wife, betook himſelf to another woman, at leaſt to too much familiarity with her, and is now a Souldier in one of the Gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of this County, from whence he wrote the <hi>Letter</hi> I mention to the woman, whom, forſaking his wife, he had ſo much followed. This <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> by ſome means intercepted, from the Original of it, by a ſpecial friend imparted to me, I tranſcribed the whole of it: the name of this perſon, and place where he is, I ſhall forbear, for ſome Reaſons, to mention; but the truth of what I here inſert, is too notoriouſly known by divers in theſe parts, to whom this Relation will come; nor ſhall I ſet down the whole of the <hi>Letter,</hi> but onely that part of it, which relates to the buſineſs I am upon: And it is thus:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Well, I am filled with the quickening Spirit, and with the Holy Ghoſt; and I hope ere long to enjoy that Light I told you of: For here is</hi> Elias <hi>flying in his fiery Charet. Already ſtrange things are done about</hi> Ando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>and</hi> Wincheſter: <hi>many mens hearts fail them for fear; for there is one who ſaith, he is</hi> Chriſt, <hi>and with Him the Lady</hi> Mary, <hi>who declares ſtrange things: They never miſs to make trumpets ſound in the very bellies of their Converts, and great ſhips appear to the view of all people neer them. If they deſire to ſpeak with an one whom they never before ſaw, if they ſpeak to any to go for them, they muſt, and cannot refrain, when that they ſend for them; and meſſenger and all come, though they go five or ſix miles, they come again in half an hour. Lights appear up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the breſts of many: let them diſcourſe with whom they will, Priests or elſe, they all are converted, leave all, and follow them: For the moſt
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:117821:24"/>part it is thought they have converted to them five or ſix hundred; and now they are in</hi> Wincheſter <hi>Priſon: and ſince that, He hath been ſeen amongst his members, many of them; I ſay,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Lyes &amp; all.</note> 
                     <hi>He hath been ſeen amongst them in appearance, and yet His Body all the while in the Priſon, with a hundred more of the like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which here I cannot declare.</hi> Thus far the <hi>Letter,</hi> the Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereof was with this ſubſcription:</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>From and to all Eternity, Thine own ſelf, MALLANCHOLIC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>With this Verſe alſo at the foot of the Letter.</p>
                     <q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>'Cauſe God in Ginger I do uſe to own,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The Holy Crew great love to me have ſhown.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>By this paſſage of the <hi>Letter,</hi> notwithſtanding that moſt of the Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars are notorious lyes and falſhoods; and if they were truths, I mean, that ſuch things had been ſeen and done, yet could prove nothing, unleſs that this deceivers coming was ſuch as our Saviour hath fore-told ſhould be the coming of the falſe Chriſts in the latter times of the world, with ſigns and lying wonders, whereby if poſsible to deceive the very Elect: yet it hereby appears with what falſe reports the hearts of this wicked party abroad were yet ſupported.</p>
            <p>Among the many that viſited theſe perſons in this the time of their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoment, I acknowledg my ſelf to be one, who (ſtill with ſome othess with me) went ſeveral times to them, and had as often conference with them: I have reſerved by me in writing the ſubſtance of what in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe paſſed between us, which I ſhall not now relate, onely ſomething in general concerning either of them.</p>
            <p>As for the man <hi>William Franklin,</hi> I found it very hard at all to deal with him; for he carried himſelf very warily, jealous of me (or any, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs well known to him) eſpecially if there were any elſe in company; as if there coming were to entrap him, and learn ſomewhat againſt him: He is naturally very ſlow of ſpeech, but now he was very ſhy of deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf at all; but in that diſcourſe I could obtain with him, I heard ſome complaints fall from him of the trouble he was now in, but very little that might diſcover any true ſence of the great evil he had commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, of which I laboured chiefly to make him ſenſible: yea, ſo far, for ought I could ever perceive, of being ſenſible thereof, that he rather la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bored to put it off, to deny it, to make it to be but the miſtakes of others, that he ſhould ſay he was indeed a Son of God, but never to have affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf to be the Son of God. No particular acknowledgment of any thing could be got from him, onely he would in general ſay, <hi>If I have
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:117821:25"/>done any man wrong, if I have deceived any one, I ſhall be ſorry for it:</hi> and ſo ſheltered himſelf under ſuch generals as theſe, without any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular acknowledgment at all, notwithſtanding he had in his <hi>Recantation</hi> under his own hand confeſſed the ſubſtance of what he was by any charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. In what related to Religion he appeared very ignorant, even in the Principles of it, but very plauſible in his ſpeech, that might eaſily inſinuate it ſelf into the mindes of the ſimple; his ſpeech and language was wholy according to the Familiſts Dialect, from whom I ſuppoſe he had ſucked in all theſe wicked Principles, upon which he was acted: He would often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times alledg Scripture in his diſcourſe, and ſpeak much in the language of it, but very ſtrangely abuſing, perverting, wreſting it from the true ſence thereof by his Allegorical fancies.</p>
            <p>But as for the woman <hi>M: Gadbury,</hi> ſhe was more free, but very uncertain in her diſcourſe; ſometimes ſhe would ſeem to plead ſomewhat for the things wherewith ſhe was charged: for her accompanying with <hi>Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> lying with him, and the appearance of Adultery and uncleanneſs that was in it, I heard her alledg that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Have I not power to lead about a ſiſter, a wife, &amp;c.</hi> And it is remarkable what was told me by a godly Miniſter, to be ſpoken by her unto him, when he asked whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhe were not aſhamed of it, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>Adam and Eve in innocency were naked, and were not aſhamed; but ſin brought ſhame into the world: but when they come to be in Chriſt, it is again taken away.</hi> For <hi>William Franklins</hi> being Chriſt, ſhe would plead the union of the Saints and Chriſt together: But at other times, eſpecially after ſhe had been a little time in <hi>Bridewel,</hi> and was thence removed to the Gaol, ſhe would ſeem with tears to lament her condition, and the trouble ſhe was in; and would ſeem heartily to acknowledg how much ſhe had been deceived, and had given the glory of God and Chriſt to another; That it was well with her till ſhe looked down upon the creature, and had reſpect to <hi>Franklin,</hi> by whom ſhe would ſay, ſhe was deceived, even undone by him, and lay all the blame upon him; and that ſhe ſhould not endure to look upon him any more: But after a little time of her being in Priſon with him, ſhe began again to look upon him, and be too familiar with him: But even then, when ſhe ſeemed moſt to acknowledg her evils, and how much ſhe had been deceived, yet ſhe would ſtill ſtick to thoſe Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Revelations ſhe had related, that they were not of <hi>Satan,</hi> not deluſions, but of God; it was the Voyce of Jehovah ſpake ſo to her: all the world ſhould not take her off from it. And though both I and others in this labored much with her, to make her ſenſible that theſe were deceits, and rehearſed many of them, and declared how contrary for matter and end, and unlike in manner, to Gods revealing himſelf to his
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:117821:25"/>people they were, that if ſhe acknowledged (as ſhe did) <hi>Franklin</hi> to be a deceiver, her ſelf to be deluded by him, ſhe might wel ſee theſe to be deceits and to be of the Devil, which had ſo bin the means to draw her from Chriſt to give her ſelf to another: That this was her firſt error and inlet to all the reſt, her ſlighting Scripture to hearken to theſe deceits; and though ſhe did recover from this, ſhe might be as apt to fall into the like evil again, ſo long as ſuch ways of Revelation, beſides and contrary to the Scripture, were reſpected by her; and with theſe and ſuch like Arguments was ſhe often perſwaded, but nothing would in this prevail, but ſhe would ſtand it out even to the death thoſe Viſions to be of God; by all which may be eaſily diſcerned what little opinion is to be had of her feigned Recantation, and how ſoon ſhe may be expected to fall again into the like or greater evils, when that corrupt principle of giving heed to ſuch wicked Viſions and Revelations ſhall be ſo tenaciouſly held and aſſerted by her.</p>
            <p>Thus theſe perſons abiding in priſon, at length the Aſſize comes, which began here on Thurſday, <hi>March</hi> 7. and upon Friday, <hi>March</hi> 8. in the morning, were both theſe perſons preſented at the Bar, before the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Rolls,</hi> then one of the Judges for this Weſtern Circuit, and who here ſate upon thoſe buſineſſes which relate to life and death. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Franklin</hi> was firſt proceeded withall; but the buſineſs with him held not much debate, he renounced what he was charged withall, denyed himſelf now to be <hi>the Chriſt,</hi> declared that he deſired to be a Member of that Body whereof Chriſt is the Head, and hoped to be ſaved by him; he moreover declared himſelf (yet but in general according to his manner) to be ſorry for his Errors, and what he had done amiſs; his Recantation, before mentioned, was then again preſented to him, and owned by him, and in the face of the whole Court he ſubſcribed thereunto. And this was all that I could learn by way of Examination, or Tryal, to be done with him, for I was not preſent at it; but I came time enough to ſee and hear the proceedings which followed with <hi>Mary Gadbury,</hi> and the other perſons, Mr <hi>Woodward, Spradbury, Dixon,</hi> who, as hath been before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, were bound over to the Aſſize. <hi>Mary Gadbury</hi> being preſented at the Bar, and now both <hi>Franklin</hi> and ſhe ſtanding there together, the Informations were read, which were given into the Iuſtices, and which I have before ſet down; divers Witneſſes of credit did there alſo <hi>Viva voce</hi> deliver to the Iudg what they knew in the buſineſs, and ſome confirmed upon Oath what was before teſtified by them to the Iuſtices, and ſome ſpake more fully to what theſe perſons were charged withall: eſpecially the Conſtable, who ſerved the Warant upon them, whereby they were apprehended, he teſtified, that <hi>Franklin</hi> told him concerning himſelf, <hi>that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:117821:26"/>he was Chriſt, the Saviour of the world, who dyed on the Croſs for the ſins of the people, that he was Alpha and Omega, and that he who believed in him ſhould be ſaved:</hi> And that when he came to ſerve his Warrant upon them, they asked him, <hi>how he durſt be ſo bold as to come in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord, and bid him put his ſhooes from off his feet, for the place whereon he ſtood was holy ground.</hi> And that at that time, looking in up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and ſeeing them in bed between the ſheets together, they check<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him for being ſo bold as to ſee them there: He alſo witneſſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the woman, that ſhe ſaid of her ſelf, that ſhe was <hi>Mary the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Chriſt, who bare this Chriſt; and that ſhe was the woman clothed with the Sun, and the Moon under her feet:</hi> He alſo witneſſed, That Mr <hi>Woodward</hi> layed open to him the Image of <hi>Daniel,</hi> to perſwade him (had he not had more grace then to believe it) to be of their opinion: Divers other things were alſo witneſſed concerning <hi>Mary Gadbury,</hi> as that ſhe ſhould ſay of <hi>Franklin,</hi> That ſhe had no other husband after the fleſh but him, nor he any other wife but her ſelf; ſhe denyed not but another wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man might lay claim to him, but no one could ſay he was her husband, but her ſelf: Other Teſtimonies being the ſame with what hath been before related, I forbear to proceed in farther Relation of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mary Gadbury</hi> having now obtained liberty to ſpeak for her ſelf, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, That ſhe had indeed believed otherwiſe concerning <hi>Franklin</hi> then now ſhe did, for ſhe followed him not as <hi>Franklin,</hi> as now ſhe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives him to be: But as concerning her lying with him, concerning which many queſtions were asked her of the reaſon of it, &amp; ſhe rebuked as guilty of adultery in it; ſhe anſwered, to free her ſelf from being account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a harlot, That <hi>Franklin</hi> had denyed to her that he had any wife and children, and that he knew not ſuch fleſhly relation, that ſhe companied not with him as a carnal, but as a ſpiritual man, and ſhe denyed any whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom whatſoever, forſhe companied not with him for camal copulation, nor was there any ſuch between them; ſhe companied not with him in an upcivil way, but as a fellow-feeler of her miſery; at which laſt word the whole Court laughed exceedingly, ſome ſaying, <hi>Yea, we think you companied with him as a fellow-feeler indeed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> She having thus ſpoken, the Judg declared, with much deteſtation, the evil of theſe opinions and practiſes, That the opinions were ſo groſs, that it could not be believed any one in his wits could follow them, but eſpecially wondering at this of a Miniſters being ſeduced by them: And for what ſhe alledged of her not lying with him as a carnal, but as a ſpiritual man, he ſaid, That ſo might any whore ſay the like, and might this be allowed her, pretend the like conceit to colour any adultery and whoredom whatſoever; that in all this ſhe ſhewed her ſelf to be a lewd woman, and that Bridewell was too
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:117821:26"/>good for her: In fine, this at length was the ſentence of the Iudg con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning either of theſe, That <hi>Franklin</hi> ſhould lie in Gaol till he give good ſecurity for his good behaviour; and that the women be committed to Bridewell, and there lie till the next Quarter Seſſions: And though the woman pleaded that ſhe might not be puniſhed twice for the ſame of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, having been before in Bridewell; yet could ſhe not get it remitted, but was rather told, That the puniſhment was too light for ſuch a lewd woman; and her offence was the greater<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> becauſe ſhe ſo committed it under the cloak of Religion. She alſo preſented a <hi>Petition</hi> to the Iudg, which though her releaſe could not be obtained by it as ſhe deſired, yet becauſe it is an Acknowledgment of the ſubſtance of what hath been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore related concerning her, I ſhall here inſert it.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="petition">
                        <head>To the Right Honorable the Lord Chief Justice <hi>Rouls,</hi> and Justice <hi>Nicholls.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <head type="sub">The humble Petition of <hi>Mary Gadbury,</hi> lately living in Watling-ſtreet.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>THat your Petitioner, who hath ever lived in honeſt converſation, and in good repute amongst her neighbors, and all that ever knew her, living religiouſly amongst them, as they do hereby teſtifie for her the ſame by their hands hereunder written, until by the means of a woman who lodged in your Petitioners houſe, who brought one</hi> Franklin <hi>unto her, who moſt falſly feigned himſelf to be Chriſt, by whoſe vehement perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions (he ſhewing her Scripture for his falſe pretences) your Petitioner was ſeduced (he forcibly perſwading her) to believe in him, and to ſell all that ſhe had, and follow him, as her Chriſt and Saviour, which your Petitioner did, and now ſhe is by his means utterly undone, and caſt into Bridewell, a priſoner there at</hi> Wincheſter.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>In compaſſion of the premiſſes, and your Petitioners contrition, and great ſorrow of heart for her ſaid offence, ſhe in all humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity humbly beſeecheth, that your Lordſhips will be pleaſed that ſhe may be relieved in the ſame, and that your Peticioner may by your charitable goodneſs be releaſed out of the ſaid priſon.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>But not able to obtain her deſired liberty by this her Petition, let us leave her to her ſentence for Bridewell, and <hi>Franklin</hi> for the Gaol, and conſider what was likewiſe done with the other parties.</p>
            <p>After this proceeding with theſe perſons, Mr <hi>Woodward</hi> was called, who at firſt denyed his owning of <hi>Franklin</hi> to be Chriſt; but divers
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:117821:27"/>things were teſtified againſt him concerning it: in particular Mr <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prat</hi> did there again deliver upon oath before the Judg, what he had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly teſtified concerning him and others of them to the Juſtices; and he himſelf, after many queſtions that paſſed forcing him thereto, at length largely confeſſed what of Viſions and Voyces he had ſeen and heard, and how he had been ſeduced by them; adding withall, in anſwer to a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion by the Iudg propoſed to him, That he thought there was jugling in the buſineſs: The ſentence at length pronounced againſt him was the ſame with <hi>Franklins,</hi> That he be committed to the Gaol, there to lie till he bring in good ſecurity for his good behaviour: And becauſe it was proved, that it was known to him and his wife, that <hi>Franklin</hi> was a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried man, and yet he entertained theſe perſons in an adulterous way, lying together in his houſe, it was ordered by the Iudg, That Mrs <hi>Woodward,</hi> his wife, be indicted for a Bawd, the Indictment delivered to the Grand Iury was found by them, and ſhe not being then preſent to anſwer it, he was bound to bring her in to anſwer it at the next Aſſize: and as I have been well informed, his living or Parſonage was by Order of the Committee afterward, and that very juſtly, ſequeſtred from him, to be given to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.</p>
            <p>After Mr <hi>Woodward,</hi> were <hi>Edward Spradbury</hi> and <hi>Henry Dixon</hi> call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and both alſo appeared: <hi>Dixons</hi> Examination before the Iuſtices, wherein he had affirmed <hi>Franklin</hi> to be the Son of God, was read; he acknowledged he had ſaid ſo, but that he did find it otherwiſe now: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing asked whether he were one of the deſtroying Angels, as he had before affirmed himſelf to be, he anſwered, that he was not, and now acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged that he was <hi>Harry Dixon</hi> of <hi>Stockbridg,</hi> and not ſuch a perſon. <hi>Spradbury</hi> alſo being asked whether <hi>Franklin</hi> were the Meſſiah, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged that he did ſometimes ſay ſo, but would not now affirm him to be ſo: At length both of theſe received the ſame ſentence that <hi>Will: Franklin</hi> and Mr <hi>Woodward</hi> before them had, <hi>(viz.)</hi> To be committed to Gaol, and there to lie, till they put in good ſecurity for their good beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour; and accordingly Mr <hi>Woodward, Spradbury, Dixon,</hi> are preſently ſeized on by the Gaoler, and taken by him into his cuſtody. And thus you have the Tryals and Cenſures of theſe ſeveral perſons: Theſe three laſt, Mr <hi>Woodward, Spradbury</hi> and <hi>Dixon,</hi> being acquainted in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, lay not long in priſon, but the ſame day wherein they were commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, offered ſuch ſecurity which would be bound for them, and which was accepted, and were accordingly the ſame day releaſed. <hi>Mary Gad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> was according to order taken to Bridewell, and received correction there again, according to the order of the houſe, where alſo ſhe continued till the Quarter Seſſions holden here the week after <hi>Eaſter,</hi> at which time
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:117821:27"/>petitioning with tears to the Iuſtices for her liberty, acknowledging alſo publiquely her errors and wickedneſs, ſhe was diſcharged by them; and the week after (the laſt week, on Munday, <hi>April</hi> 22. 1650.) ſhe went from this City of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> towards <hi>London,</hi> in the Wagon which weekly travelleth between theſe places: But <hi>William Franklin</hi> not ſo acquainted in the Country, and his crime ſo great, that there is none but would be aſhamed to be bound for him, lies in priſon yet, is there at this preſent, not being yet able to find ſuch ſufficient ſecurity that may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted; and how much longer he may continue there, is to me altogether unknown.</p>
            <p>Thus have I now preſented my Reader with a true, faithful, impartial Relation of the doings and ſufferings of theſe Blaſphemers; in reſpect of the things done, rather then of what they ſuffered indeed, a tragical ſtory. I ſhall now conclude the Relation it ſelf with preſenting to my Reader a brief Synopſis of it, in the names of the Actors in it, with the parts acted by them therein; which were,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Franklin,</hi> Blaſphemouſly making himſelf to be <hi>The Chriſt, the Meſſias, the Saviour of the world, crucified for the ſins of the people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mary Gadbury,</hi> as blaſphemouſly called, and calling her ſelf, <hi>The Spouſe of Chriſt, the Bride, the Lambs Wife, the Lady, the Queen, the Mother of Chriſt that bears him, the woman clothed with the Sun, who travels in birth for the bringing forth of thoſe ſpiritually that were ſeduced by them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Goody <hi>Waterman,</hi> The <hi>Kings daughter all glorious within.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr <hi>William Woodward,</hi> a Miniſter, their Proſelyte, who profeſſed he <hi>ſaw his glory, and rejoyced to ſee it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mrs <hi>Woodward,</hi> his wife, <hi>The Elect Lady.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Noyce, John the Baptiſt,</hi> whoſe office was to declare the coming of this counterfeit Chriſt into the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edward Spradbury,</hi> One of the <hi>two Witneſſes,</hi> and an <hi>healing Angel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry Dixon,</hi> One of the <hi>deſtroying Angels,</hi> whoſe office it was to be ſent forth to curſe and deſtroy the Earth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Holmes,</hi> junior, Another <hi>destroying Angel,</hi> ſent forth alſo to curſe and deſtroy the Earth. Divers other perſons alſo there were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in this wicked buſineſs, of whom not having ſuch clear and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Information, I have not inſerted their names in this Relation.</p>
            <p>And having thus concluded the Relation it ſelf, let me deſire of every one to whom it ſhall come, and who ſhall be the Reader of it, to conſider ſeriouſly with himſelf, whether he hath ever known, read or heard of the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:117821:28"/>like abominations to be acted in the World. How great muſt this wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs needs be, for men profeſſing the Name and Goſpel of Chriſt, and ſo eminent in the profeſſion of it as ſome of theſe ſometimes were, not onely to depart from Chriſt and renounce him, (for how could theſe things have been acted by theſe perſons without a manifeſt denying of Chriſt, renouncing the Faith, and reckoning to be even a fable whatſoever the <hi>Scripture</hi> hath recorded concerning him?) but alſo to proclaim, and ſet up another in his ſtead, to be <hi>the Chriſt;</hi> and to aſcribe to ſuch a perſon whatſoever is due and proper to Chriſt; and for ſuch an one to aſſert him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be the Chriſt, and all of them to aſſume ſo wickedly ſuch Titles and Offices to themſelves in the ſervice of him. Surely what <hi>Sleidan</hi> hath reported in the tenth Book of his <hi>Commentaries,</hi> concerning the blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Opinions, ſpeeches, and practices of <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leiden,</hi> and the <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterian Anabaptists,</hi> is nothing in compariſon of the things I have here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated concerning theſe perſons. <hi>David George, Tho: Muncer, William Hacket,</hi> came very ſhort in their Blaſphemies and Wickedneſſes, to what hath thus been by theſe acted. And had they not, together with their blaſphemous Opinions, faln into ſuch wicked practices, as might deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly bring them under the cenſure of the Magiſtrate, and were ſo ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y taken notice of, and a ſtop put to their wickedneſs by them, what the ſad effects of theſe their ways might have been, is eaſie to be imagined. We have heard of many ſtrange and blaſphemous Opinions vented abroad in theſe times of ours, but ſurely never any came to ſuch an high degree of blaſphemy (that ever I could hear of) as theſe perſons have done. In all which there is ſurely much to be learned by us; great uſe may be made of this Relation for our Inſtructions: and ſuch remarkable paſſages, as are here repreſented, ought not to paſs us without ſome ſerious conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of them, and of the uſe and benefit we are to receive from them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Here may we learn by experience the Truth of Chriſt, and of his Word, the Scriptures; for how are we fore-warned by them, (O that we might all be thereby alſo fore-armed,) <hi>that there ſhall come falſe Chriſts, and that they ſhall come with ſigns and lying wonders; that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhall be deceived by them: That men ſhall creep in cunningly, who ſhall privily bring in damnable Hereſies, denying the Lord that bought them:</hi> All which we may ſee, even to the letter, verifled in this <hi>Relation:</hi> So that theſe perſons, thus eminently fulfilling the <hi>Scripture,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their impugning of it, give us ground thereby to be ſetled in our faith concerning the divine Authority of it.</p>
            <p>Here is the patience and long-ſuffering of God to be admired! who, notwithſtanding he be ſo jealous of his glory, that he will not give it to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:117821:28"/>another, nor communicate to any other beſides that Authority which he hath given to the Son, whom he hath exalted and anointed to be both Lord and Chriſt, ſhould yet exerciſe ſuch forbearance towards perſons ſo extreamly guilty in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſe their actions of ſuch high affront, yea, Treaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Divine Majeſty; not only denying to his Son the glory to which he is exalted, which every knee is by his Command to bow unto; but alſo invading it, aſſuming it to themſelves, ſetting up another in his ſtead, aſcribing to him what is due and proper to Chriſt. O that this pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, forbearance, and long-ſuffering of God might lead thoſe to whom it hath thus been ſhewn, to true Repentance of thoſe great Treaſons, which, againſt the Majeſty of himſelf, and Son, they have thus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</p>
            <p>Tremble we at the Example of Divine Juſtice we here finde diſcovered: Wherein is the Juſtice of God more ſeen, then in his ſpiritual Judgments, of all Judgments the greateſt? <hi>By God were the Gentiles given up to the luſts of their hearts, to all uncleanneſs, to diſhonor their bodies, to a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate minde, to do things not convenient, &amp;c.</hi> whereby they became ſo guilty of all theſe evils recorded concerning them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.24, 28, 29. And all <hi>this, becauſe knowing God in his Works, they yet glorified him not as God, nor gave thanks to him, Verſ.</hi> 21. By God were the <hi>Apostati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Chriſtians</hi> under the Papacy given up unto <hi>ſtrong deluſions, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve all the lyes of the man of ſin;</hi> and this in Judgment alſo, for their retaining the Truth in unrighteouſneſs, <hi>not bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eving the Truth, but taking pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.11, 12. So how could it be, that any perſons ſhould be ſo groſly deceived, for any one ſo to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce Chriſt, as to ſet up himſelf in his ſtead? or for any others to harken to ſuch manifeſt dece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s, and to give up themſelves, and their faith, to ſuch a deceiver, were there not the juſt Judgment of God giving them up in Judgment thereunto, and ſome great, though poſſibly ſecret evil, the cauſe of it. By all which we may ſee, that if God in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment leave perſons to themſelves, there is no evil ſo great, which they would not ſuddenly, by the power of inward corruption, and of <hi>Satans temptation,</hi> fall into, ſo as to be led about by <hi>Satan</hi> at his will, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his Inſtrument, even in the greateſt wickedneſſes.</p>
            <p>In this <hi>Relation</hi> there hath been much diſcovered from the Confeſſions of the perſons themſelves of Viſions, Revelations, Voyces, which they pretend unto, to have been ſeen and heard by them; but whether any ſuch things have been ſo ſeen and heard by them, as by them is reported, hath been by ſome queſtioned; apprehending all theſe their Relations of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:117821:29"/>them to have been onely by themſelves deviſed, to deceive the better by them. I deny not but ſuch things may have been ſeen and heard by them which they have related; which ſome, who have endevored to take as neer a conſideration of them as may be, have imput<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to witchcraft, and a ſecret compact with the Devil therein: But this I dare confidently aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert concerning them, That being for the matter and manner of them ſo unlike to any the dealings of God with his ſervants, yea, even then, when by Viſions and ſuch like ways he made himſelf and his Will known to them; (and therefore I deſire the <hi>Reader</hi> to conſider either, and compare them together;) and the end of them being ſo manifeſtly wicked, as to cauſe men to ſlight the Word, and have it in contempt, paſſing that by, to harken to theſe things; tending alſo to draw men from Chriſt, and to ſet up a Deceiver in his ſtead, to deſtroy, and not to confirm the faith of any; and this to have been in ſome the effect of them, that therefore ſurely they were not of God, but of the Devil, the father of lyes, who hath thus deceived by them: And for the Devil to be able to effect and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſuch things to the fancy and ſenſes of men, and to have done thus with others, and by ſuch means deceived men, is I ſuppoſe, even to all unqueſtionable, that I need not go about the proof of it. Diſcern we then here ſomewhat of the <hi>wiles</hi> of this our <hi>ſpiritual Enemy:</hi> The per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons he chooſeth thus to deal withall were ſuch as ſlighted the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and inclined to ſuch things as <hi>theſe;</hi> eaſie therefore to be deceived by them: and ſuch are the <hi>perſons</hi> the <hi>Devil</hi> doth uſually make choyce of to deal in ſuch a way withall; and in all <hi>theſe Revelations</hi> is the <hi>Scripture</hi> yet made uſe of, though in the whole of it miſapplied: Almoſt all is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in <hi>Scripture-phraſe, language, and expreſſion.</hi> The <hi>Devil</hi> thus transforming <hi>himſelf into an Angel of light,</hi> thereby the better to deceive them, and others by them. What a warning may this be to many in <hi>theſe times,</hi> with whom the <hi>Scripture;</hi> are ſo much in contempt, that they look on them as low things, themſelves above them; and ſet up a <hi>teaching of the Spirit within themſelves,</hi> without beſides, againſt, and contrary to them: and are ready to entertain, what, under the notion of <hi>Enthuſiaſms and Revelations,</hi> ſhall be brought to them. When once <hi>perſons</hi> are come to ſuch a ſlighting of <hi>the Scripture,</hi> then are they, if not <hi>paſt hope of recovery,</hi> yet certainly <hi>in the ſnare of the Devil, too fast entangled by him, and in the road way of Error:</hi> nor can they have in <hi>themſelves</hi> any <hi>ſecurity</hi> at all from being <hi>carried away with the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt deceits and deluſions.</hi> Conſider <hi>the Jews and Papists,</hi> ſetting up <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon and the Ark, their Talmud and unwritten Traditions, with the holy Scripture:</hi> and while they accuſe the <hi>Scripture</hi> of <hi>imperfection, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity, &amp;c.</hi> make it by <hi>theſe</hi> to be ſupplied, by <hi>theſe</hi> to be explained;
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:117821:29"/>how hath God viſited theſe? giving up the one to a <hi>ſpirit of ſlumber, to have eyes not to ſee, and ears not to hear, unto this day:</hi> not more Vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonds through the Earth in their Converſation, then in their Opinions, in reſpect of the vanity and uncertainty of them; and even when <hi>Meſes</hi> is read a vail is upon their Underſtandings: and giving up the other alſo to <hi>ſtrong deluſions, to beleeve lyes, to give heed to lying ſpirits, and doctrines of Devils.</hi> Conſider the <hi>Germane Munſterian Anabaptists</hi> in their time, as much neglecting <hi>Scripture,</hi> and ſetting up <hi>Revelations,</hi> which they much pretended unto, given up by God to act ſuch abominations, which have made <hi>the remembrance of them</hi> odious to all poſterity that hath heard of them. The great ſin of <hi>ſlighting, contemning the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the Word of God,</hi> is never left unviſited, unpuniſhed by God; Viſited it is, not onely with an uncertainty in matters of Religion, that having left <hi>this pillar and Cloud of fire</hi> which ſhould <hi>guide them through the Deſart of this world,</hi> they are as <hi>men wandering in a Wilderneſs, where no way is;</hi> like <hi>Cain,</hi> in reſpect of Religion Vagabonds, ſetled in nothing, <hi>carryed up and down with every wind of Doctrine,</hi> conſtant and certain in nothing but inconſtancy and uncertainty; and alſo at length given up to the groſſeſt <hi>deceits and deluſions</hi> which the Examples of many in theſe times, as well as of the perſons I have here had to do withall, may evidence to us: For having left this <hi>certain light of the Sun of the Word,</hi> the <hi>Ignes Fatui,</hi> which they follow, never leave them till they have plunged them into ſome pit or other. Greater meaſure of light and ſpiritual enjoyment theſe men uſually pretend for this; but, as the Apoſtle ſaith of <hi>the Gentiles, Rom.</hi> 1. <hi>Pretending to be wiſe, they became fooliſh:</hi> ſo are theſe very carnal, wherein they pretend to be ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, and are ſo diſcovered to be by <hi>the light of the Word</hi> in their moſt <hi>ſpiritual notions,</hi> by <hi>every ſpiritual Christian,</hi> that ſo it may be truly ſaid unto them, and of them, <hi>They have rejected the Word of the Lord, and what Wiſdom is in them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the conſideration of theſe many ſad Examples of <hi>Divine Juſtice,</hi> upon the <hi>Contemners of the Word,</hi> may not ſuffice to reclaim thoſe that are already plunged in the guilt of this evil, yet I hope they may ſerve to warn thoſe who are yet free from this contagion, eſpecially <hi>all the people of God,</hi> that they <hi>take heed how they fall into it, and thereby into tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the ſnare of the Devil;</hi> but rather let this of the Divine Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, Perfection, Sufficiency of the <hi>Scriptures</hi> be, as well as the firſt Principle, for the Foundation of our Faith, that is learned and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by us, which the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> directs us to, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20. <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this firſt of all: That holy men of God ſpake as they were moved by
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:117821:30"/>the Holy Ghoſt:</hi> and therefore what they ſpake, and is from them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in the <hi>Scriptures</hi> to be of Divine Authority, I would put the Emphaſis on, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Knowing it firſt of all;</hi> as if it were that Principle which is firſt to be received by us: So let this Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple be conſtantly cleaved to, that we receive nothing in matters of Faith and Religion, but what we have from it; For if once we fall from this, we fall from all. Look not then after <hi>new Revelations,</hi> but <hi>hear what the Spirit ſpeaks in the Scripture to the Churches.</hi> And by this <hi>Word of Truth try all things; Try the ſpirits, whether they are of God; for now are there many falſe ſpirits gone abroad into the world.</hi> Surely they are but <hi>deceitful Merchants,</hi> and ſuch is the ware they bring unto us, which they will not endure to be brought to this light to be tryed. Cauſe we have to be very jealous, <hi>That that ſilver is reprobate, counterfeit, droſſie,</hi> which they would obtrude upon us, not ſuffering it to be tryed by this Touchſtone: <hi>To the Law, and to the Teſtimony; they who ſpeak not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this, it is becauſe there is no light in them.</hi> And be as diligent to enquire after the ſence, as well as words of Scripture, leſt by the words, contrary to the true ſence, we be deceived.</p>
            <p>From what hath been held out in this <hi>Relation,</hi> may divers receive ſome warning to themſelves in other things, beſides what are now men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned.</p>
            <p>Firſt, To the perſons themſelves, the <hi>Agents and Inſtruments</hi> in this <hi>great evil,</hi> let them conſider <hi>whence they have fallen, and repent:</hi> Conſider <hi>the greatneſs of their ſin</hi> by <hi>the fearful aggravations which it will admit;</hi> For one to aſſert himſelf to be <hi>the Chriſt,</hi> and others to declare him ſo to be, are they not both guilty of the <hi>higheſt Treaſon</hi> that can be imaginable againſt <hi>the King of Heaven?</hi> and while they endevor to perſwade others to joyn with them in <hi>theſe their evil ways,</hi> is it not to draw <hi>ſubjects</hi> from <hi>their allegiance,</hi> to <hi>deſtroy their Faith,</hi> and <hi>murther their Souls thereby.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Surely they have preached <hi>another Jeſus, another Gospel,</hi> then what <hi>Paul</hi> preached; let them therefore conſider whether they come not under that Curſe which is by him againſt ſuch denounced, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8, 9. Cauſe they have enough with <hi>Peter</hi> to weep bitterly for this ſo <hi>great an evil;</hi> and <hi>to look up to that Jeſus whom they have pierced, by whom alone they muſt be ſaved from the guilt of that Treaſon which against him they have committed:</hi> Let them alſo take heed they return no more to this or the like folly, leſt <hi>their latter end be worſe then their beginning.</hi> And though I may be likely to incur ſome diſpleaſure from them, for thus pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:117821:30"/>
               <hi>their names and actions,</hi> yet, if there be in them any <hi>true ſight, and deteſtation of theſe wickedneſſes wrought in their hearts,</hi> they will not be much diſpleaſed at the publiſhing of it, for the warning of others by <hi>their example,</hi> but be alſo provoked hereby to make as publique De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of <hi>their Repentance,</hi> as publique notice hath been taken of the ſin committed by them.</p>
            <p>Many ſuch there are who walk in that way of <hi>profeſſion,</hi> which amongſt us bears the name of <hi>Anabaptiſm,</hi> to whom alſo ſomething might here be delivered by way of warning: Of all <hi>the ſeveral ways</hi> and <hi>ſects</hi> in <hi>the profeſſion of Religion,</hi> which men, ſeparating from the <hi>Reformed Churches,</hi> have faln into ſince the time the <hi>Reformation</hi> began: I know none ſo eminently blaſted of God, that either for <hi>the Congregations of them,</hi> or <hi>particular perſons,</hi> have been given up unto, and been guilty of ſuch <hi>Errors and ſinful Practices</hi> as thoſe I now ſpeak of, not to inſtance in <hi>times past,</hi> and <hi>the practices</hi> of thoſe of this <hi>profeſſion</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> left on record by <hi>the teſtimony of thoſe who deſerve ſufficient credit with us,</hi> but only to have <hi>respect to our own times;</hi> See we not <hi>their Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> even in all places, ſhattered and broken to pieces, and that not by the hand of man, by the <hi>perſecution of any Enemies,</hi> but by <hi>the immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate hand of God,</hi> and by <hi>the diviſions which have riſen up amongst and within themſelves:</hi> that it is now a <hi>rare thing</hi> to find a <hi>Congregation of that profeſſion:</hi> ſome of them there may be yet holding together in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> but in all the Countries hereabouts, where <hi>Churches</hi> of them have been in <hi>ſeveral places erected,</hi> and where but <hi>few years</hi> ſince there hath been much and zealous diſputing for that way, there is not now, that I know of, a Church of them to be ſeen, but the <hi>members</hi> of them living in as ſcattered a divided way one from another, as may be: yea, refuſing to own that very way, for which they before ſo zealouſly conteſted, as the only way of God; even aſhamed of it, as if but a carnal Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Have not <hi>their Churches been the Nurſeries and Seminaries of all theſe many Errors which have overspread the face of our Nation?</hi> that from them have moſtly proceeded, and bin ſent forth, <hi>all theſe falſe teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> the <hi>Inſtruments</hi> of divulging of them: <hi>Antitrinitarianiſm, Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianiſm, Socinianiſm, &amp;c.</hi> with many other groſs <hi>Hereſies,</hi> how have they been profeſſed in them? where have the <hi>Scriptures</hi> been ſo much ſlighted, and <hi>Revelations</hi> cryed up, as among them? and for <hi>Revelations</hi> how much have they pretended to them? eſpecially when their deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful pretence of ſhaking fits was ſo much in faſhion of late amongſt them? And ſo from this ſlighting the Word of God have faln into all manner of Errors whatſoever.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:117821:31"/>
            <p>From them alſo have proceeded thoſe very Deceivers, whoſe deceits and wickedneſſes I have here related. <hi>William Franklin</hi> was ſometime a zealous Profeſſor of that way; ſo was <hi>Edward Spradbury,</hi> Mrs <hi>Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> and many others of them: yea, it hath been obſerved amongſt us, that ſcarce any appeared to harken to theſe Deceivers, to countenance them, and incline to their deceits, but ſuch who had been this way engaged. In a publique Diſpute, publiquely managed in the Church at <hi>Bazingstoke</hi> in this County, in the beginning of <hi>November</hi> laſt, by ſome godly Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of this County (with whom I was then ſomewhat engaged in the ſame cauſe with them) in behalf of Infant-Baptiſm, I ſaw <hi>Edward Sprad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> there appear, and heard him ſpeak in oppoſition to us; Mrs <hi>Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> alſo (as I have been informed) was there, and privately ſpake, to the encouraging of the parties who oppoſed us; and yet both of them, in very few weeks after, were intangled in theſe deceits, and harkened unto this Deceiver, to the even denying and renouncing of Chriſt, as hath been before related of them; and became as zealous for a time againſt thoſe who oppoſed this their counterfeit Chriſt, as they had ſo lately been againſt Infant-Baptiſm. I deny not, but ſome there are of this way of Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſm whereof I ſpeak, that I look upon as godly perſons, who hold faſt to the Scriptures, and to many fundamental doctrinal Truths delivered in them: but have they not cauſe in all theſe things to take notice of the hand of Gods Juſtice, ſo proſecuting that way of theirs; and to be very jealous, whether that way be of God, which hath been thus eminently in all times, all along, ſo blaſted by God? Yea, and farther to conſider, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be not juſt ground to judg, that their ſeparating from all the Churches of Chriſt, which are not of their opinion, and diſclaiming all fellowſhip with them as Antichriſtian, which hath generally been the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of thoſe of their way, their caſting alſo of children out of their Churches, by denying Baptiſm to them, leaving all the generation of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind in infancy in the world, the Kingdom of the Devil, not owning them to belong to the Kingdom of Heaven, the Church, but denying any thing of the free grace of God in Goſpel-Ordinances to be held out unto them, to the great undervaluing and eclipſing of that abundance of the grace of God now in the Goſpel held out unto us: Whether, I ſay, theſe be not the ſins which God hath thus viſited upon them, in his thus blaſting their way, and giving up the moſt eminent Profeſſors of it to theſe ways of deluſion? For ſurely God is jealous of the glory of his Grace, and will not endure it to be undervalued; very tender of his Churches, and of the little ones in them, that he will not ſuffer thoſe, who ſo cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fure the one, and ſo highly offend againſt the priviledges of the other, to paſs unpuniſhed. Oh that therefore theſe things might be ſo conſidered
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:117821:31"/>by theſe perſons, that the warning they have in them might be ſeriouſly layd to heart by them.</p>
            <p>Many there are who profeſs to expect a perſonal coming of Chriſt to raign here upon the Earth, and I deny not but ſome, eminent in learning and godlineſs, have held forth ſomewhat like thereunto; but I well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what a learned friend of mine ſaid long ſince unto me, when that opinion of <hi>Chiliaſm</hi> was firſt cryed up amongſt us, <hi>(viz.) That it might be juſt with God for ſome Deceiver under that pretence to come among them, and prevail for a time, to the deceiving of ſuch; and that this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion did hold out a ground and foundation for ſuch a deceit:</hi> I have now ſeen it ſomewhat truly verified; for this opinion hath been the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all theſe deceits, I have here related, to have been acted. <hi>Mary Gadbury</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elieves Chriſt ſhall come in the fleſh to raign here; ſhe asks of <hi>William Franklin</hi> whether it had been revealed to him; he takes the advantage to deceive by it, and ſaith, <hi>I am the man,</hi> and ſhe as quickly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves him; and through all this Relation theſe ſeem to be the things held out, That as Chriſt ſhould come to raign here on the Earth, ſo <hi>William Franklin</hi> was he, now come accordingly here to raign, and ſet up his Kingdom; nor think I that his deceits were or could be by any entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, unleſs this were firſt believed and expected by them. I hope therefore that ſuch an example as this is will make men wary how they entertain ſuch an opinion which ſeems to give ſuch an occaſion to it.</p>
            <p>But ſome there are who deſervedly are called <hi>Seekers,</hi> who, if they judg not themſelves to be above Goſpel-Ordinances of Word and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and look upon them as carnal low Adminiſtrations, yet pleaſe themſelves to live without them, cenſure all the Churches of Chriſt, who walk in the practiſe of any of his Ordinances, to be Antichriſtian; deny that there is any true Miniſtry, Churches, Sacraments, or any to be, till ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary perſon or perſons be immediately ſent of Chriſt, as Apoſtles, for the reſtoring of them: Upon which ground themſelves live without practiſe of any of theſe Ordinances, or of any Church Society, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn and cenſure thoſe who walk in the practice of them; whoſe opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion to recite is to refute, and the evil of it cannot but be eaſily diſcerned, and be alſo by all the people of God juſtly exploded, that have had in their ſouls any true experience of the benefit and comfort God gives in to the Souls of his people, who, in an humble and conſcionable manner, walk in the practiſe of his Ordinances, and attend upon them: But let them alſo conſider how eaſily they lay themſelves open to ſuch deceits, how eaſie a thing it may be for them to be deceived by any De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver, that taking the advantage of this expectation of theirs, ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend himſelf to be ſuch a one as is expected by them; yea, cauſe they have to take heed of it, that God in judgment give them not up thereunto,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:117821:32"/>for this contempt and ſlighting of his Ordinances.</p>
            <p>And may not this at laſt be warning to every one, to be jealous of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and his own ſtanding; <hi>That he who thinks he ſtand, take heed leſt he fall,</hi> ſeeing ſuch ſad examples of the great and dangerous falls of theſe and ſuch like perſons. Take we heed of an uncertainty in matters of Religion, of being Scepticks in it, affected with every novity; and Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian like, hankering in our minds after it; and beware of theſe whom we ſee poſſeſſed with ſuch a ſpirit of giddineſs in matters of Religion, that they know not what to fix or ſettle upon: See we the evil of error, how it pollutes a man: A corrupt judgment quickly cauſing a corrupt life, ſo that thoſe who cheriſh and entertain error quickly proceed to much im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety: Of which theſe perſons are alſo ſufficient examples; when once a perſon is entered into the path of error, and is fallen from his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>edfaſtneſs in the truth, he knows not where to ſettle; as appears in theſe perſons, running from one Error in Religion to another, till they at length attained to that height of blaſphemy, that I think the like hath ſearce been heard of; and uſually the proceedings of men in their changes from one Error to another, is ſtill for the worſt, according to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Evil men and Deceivers wax worſe and worſe, deceiving, and being deceived,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.13. But prize we truth, and the true knowledg of it; labour we to attain it, but labour we alſo as much to be ſetled in it, that we be not carried about with every wind of doctrine, but be rather able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for the faith againſt the gainſayers of it; hold we faſt the myſtery of Faith in a good conſcience, leſt turning aſide from the one we make ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack of the other: Surely Chriſts ſheep know the voyce of Chriſt, and can diſcern and diſtinguiſh it from the voyce of ſtrangers: The Lord make us of the number of theſe his ſheep, and give us the ointment of his Spirit, that we may know all things at leaſt that are neceſſary to be known, being guided thereby into the way of truth, we may be preſerved from the deceits of the many Antichriſts which are now abroad in the world.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:117821:32"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JOSEPH CARYL.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>May</hi> 18. 1650.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
